I have the recording odd,
so just a quick overview.
So under resources, you can
see where is my final exam,
How many people know where
their final exam is?
Awesome, Great, So maybe just
like write that down somewhere.
Write it tastes like, you know,
you're off line or something.
The day of the exam,
you'll have it in advance.
And if we arrange an alt exam,
I've recorded that there.
Right. So if that
says the wrong thing,
that means somehow I goofed
up or there's a
miscommunication.
So let me know right away if we
arrange Alt exam but it's
not represented there.
I just had an announcement
with some exam logistics.
I mean, I think it's pretty
similar to last time.
Down at the bottom,
I have a list of
all these broad topics we
covered this semester.
Of those, there's all these
different major systems.
Pytorch we did
before the midterm.
And you'd see that most of
the major systems we've covered
this semester were actually
after the mid term.
And so what I'm thinking,
I don't have the
exam finalized yet,
but I'm able to write
roughly like four or questions
for each of these five systems.
And so that would take
us to 20 questions,
which is about two
thirds of the exam.
Right? These numbers
are not fixed
and so, but kind of approximate.
And then have ten questions,
maybe other stuff,
maybe some of the
resources, you know,
maybe a question or two about
cloud stuff that we've done.
But, you know, I
think this is like
the core of what we're
doing here on this exa,
I would do that and then I
would kind of go back and make
sure you understood
all the stuff
you studied for
the durb as well,
and try to branch off for there.
Cool. So I'll open
it up for questions,
logistical or conceptual,
or I'll show you us
what I brought here.
I brought all of these
exabs from previous types,
all the worksheets,
study material.
So yeah, ask me anything.
Go for it. Yeah, right here.
Oh, oh, are you talking
about one of Oh,
I have these two, Yeah. Okay.
So these are just like
the practice question
and you are interested
in the final practice.
Okay, great. What question
do you want to look at?
Let's take a look
at 19 over here.
So question 18, 19, Okay, great.
The data owned by a node in
a decision tree has
ten rows, okay,
and five columns of feature data
in no value appears more
than what's at the table.
So how many different
ways are there that we
could split the node, right?
So for a decision tree, well,
I think that if we're trying
to split this data, right,
we could first select any of
these five columns, right?
And then if I have ten rows
and like they're sorted
or something like that,
I could choose
nine different points where
I could break it off.
So I'm going to go
with 45. Right?
So kind of nine
splits and then 45?
Yep. Yeah. Thank you
for asking. Yeah.
Other questions people have
or follow ups on that one?
Yeah. Yeah, Yeah.
I was just trying to well,
I was just like
wondering like what
if somebody said like, oh,
this column, like had all
the values were the same,
like then you
couldn't split on it.
So I was just trying to do that
to knock out like a corner case,
I would maybe let somebody
find a different answer.
Right. But that'd be, like
a little bit odd, right?
Yeah. Yeah. Thank
you for clarifying.
Yeah. Other questions
people have.
Yeah, right here. Great.
So the final exam,
question 16. Excellent. Okay.
All right, so we're
doing streaming.
So we have data that's
constantly coming in.
And as the data is coming in,
we're doing a group
by in 1 hour chunks.
Right? So I think that,
what does that mean?
That means that one
of the groups, right,
so maybe like the
groups are like this,
we have like six to 07:00 A.M.
seven to 08:00 A.M.
And then then we have
counts for these, right?
So maybe like right
now the count is,
let's say right now the
count is 12, right?
And at some point I want
to say that whatever the
count is, it's a final count.
And so this question is really
about at what point
can I say that that's
not going to change.
So I can just output it
and call it done, right?
And that really kind
of depends, right?
Like if, as all the data
is telling in the system,
like how much could
it be delayed, right?
If a sensor is offline,
like how long could it
reasonably be offline?
And so I have to, I mean,
it's a hard question, but I,
as a programmer have to
decide like how much I
think data could
be delayed, right?
And I said that I don't
think data can be
delayed more than
4 hours, right?
So 4 hours after this, right?
So this would be plus four
would end at 11:00 A.M.
All right, so if data is
never more than 4 hours late,
then at 11:00 A.M. that
town should never change.
And then I could output,
that is my final result.
And free that counter
up from memory.
Does that make sense? Yeah, so
I guess like the interval
starts at 06:00 A.M.
and it's a 1 hour
interval, right?
So that's why we have
to add in the size of
the interval to the start
of the interval, right?
Right, because at
10:30 right, I mean,
I could get a measurement
coming in for
630 and that would
change this window.
Yep. Six plus one,
and then plus four.
Yep. Mm hmm. Exactly.
Yeah. Thank you for
clarifying that.
That one touches
a lot of people.
Yep. Yeah. Other
questions people have?
Yeah, Right here. Yeah.
Let's take a look at 21.
Same exam, right? All right.
Cool. Oh, okay.
So Cassandra uses
consistent hashing,
and when it's doing
it has to have tokens.
Remember that this whole
idea of consistent hashing
is that we'd have a
token ring, maybe.
I'll just like, um, pop
it over here so we can
remind ourselves this is what
a token ring looks like.
And when we have a token
ring, we have to put nodes on
the token ring and
we have to put
rows of data on the token ring.
So that means for every
worker and every row,
we have to give it one
of these token values.
Okay?
So one of the ways we
can do that is with a
hash function, right?
We could have a
hash function that
would take some value and
then give us a token.
And that's what we
do for rows of data.
And the reason why is that if
we had some dictionary
or something like that,
that remember the token
for every row of data,
that dictionary would
be huge, right?
We might have like
billions of rows, right?
So we will just remember
the hash function.
If I see a row of data,
I can figure out
what the token is.
I don't have to look it
up in some table, right?
So we have to use it
there. We don't use
the hash function for nodes
because there's not
that many nodes.
And so we can just choose
whatever token we want.
We can just make a decision
and store it in a
dictionary somewhere.
Call the token map
and then look it up
again when we need it, right?
So the answer for this
one is trying to be
that it is only for data, right?
It uses the hash function
to get a token for data.
It uses the token map,
which is just a dictionary,
to look it up for nodes.
That makes sense. So each node
is like a worker in
the cluster, right?
So for example, right
here's node two.
And we can see
that that decision
came from up here, right?
So if somebody just decided
that that was, you know,
negative sex, Judge, how did
they choose that while
they're trying to.
So you're a node, right?
So you're a worker and
this is your token.
And you're responsible for
the rows to your immediate left.
Right? So kind of
depending on the
space spacing of the
nodes on the token ring,
you might be responsible
for more or less rows.
Right? And so Cassandra
is trying to evenly
space the tokens for
workers on the ring.
Right? That's why
it wants to choose.
And if you choose something,
rather than having like it be
a mathematical formula,
if you choose something,
then you have to remember
it in a dictionary
or some kind of data
structure, right?
So that's why we kind of
have this hybrid approach.
When we need lots and, you know,
billions of tokens
for all the rows,
it's not practical to
remember them all,
but there's not that many
workers in the cluster.
A cluster, a big cluster might
have like 1,000 workers.
A dictionary with 1,000 entries
doesn't take much memory.
Does that make
sense? Yeah, I mean,
feel free to ask a
follow up question.
I'm sure it's kind of
a tricky concept too.
So if other people
want to jump on it
too with follow ups, go for it.
Yeah, Y and value there both.
So you said, oh,
it's like you're saying
like can we think of,
could we think of like a
node being like a key maybe?
And then like the rode
being like a value maybe.
I don't normally put
in that terms though.
I could maybe see that working.
But each worker
just has to store
some rows in its local
file system, right?
Has to store that data.
So I guess it's time of
being assigned to that.
But I want to really
think it like a key in
a value because each
worker has like,
you know, many, many rows
stored on it, right?
So we're just trying
to figure out
who should do what work,
right? Does that make sense?
Yeah, Yeah.
Other questions people
have or follow ups on
that. Yeah, right here.
On the practice.
All right, question 31 on
the practice, which is here.
All right, great.
Is it stateless?
Okay, so my stream
is basically a table
that's constantly growing.
That's what a stream
is. Stream is
a constantly growing table.
And based on the query,
I can see that that table
has columns X and Y.
Okay?
And there's no aggregates here.
There's no sum or average
or anything like that.
So that means each row
can be considered
independently, right?
So if I like,
let's say I have a new x and
y value come in and it's
3.4 Then I can output seven,
even if I don't know
what the previous,
what was previously
in the table.
Right? I can treat each row
individually and that's
why it's stateless.
I don't have to
remember anything
about previous rows, right?
So this would be, this
would be stateless, right?
You could imagine I could do
a variant on this, right?
I could use like
the sum aggregate,
and then instead
of summing across
the row, I'd be
summing over a column.
Then it would be stateful.
Yeah, most aggregates
would be stateful. Right.
And the question to
ask yourself is,
if a, a new row
of data comes in,
do you have to know anything
about what has happened
previously to figure out
what the new output is?
Yeah, excellent question. Yeah,
other questions people
have. Yeah, right.
Is there any
aggregate that's not
stateless? That's
a good question.
Is there any aggregate that's
not stateless? I don't think so.
Right. I guess, I
guess by definition you're
combining multiple rows, right?
So you'd have to remember
previous rows of data, right?
So yeah, I'm going
to go with no,
I didn't thought about
it before, but I'm
going to say no,
there's no aggregate.
That's stateless.
Unless there's something
I'm over looking.
Yep. Yeah. Thank you
for clarifying that.
Putting into those terms.
Yeah. All other
questions people have.
Yeah, right here. Question
11 from the previous final.
Yeah, question 11 from
the final.
All right.
So yeah,
that was one of the
eat things about
the HDFS clusters, right?
Is that they would have
the single name node that's
responsible for metadata.
And then lots and
lots of data nodes,
maybe thousands of data nodes.
And the data nodes
are responsible for
storing the big blocks
of data, right?
You know, many gigabytes
or terabytes of data.
The name node is in charge
of taking in a path
and then figuring out,
well, what blocks do we
have corresponding
to that file path?
And then for each of
these logical blocks,
what are the
different data nodes
where we could find that data?
And so the way we talk to
HDFS is that a client will
come along and it'll say,
it'll say to the name node,
I want to read this file.
And then the name node we
respond, it'll say, okay,
here are the locations
where you can
find the blocks in
that file, right?
So, you know, there's two
ways that we could be
really overburdening
the name node, right?
I mean, if we have
lots and lots of
files and we have to remember
the names of all these files,
the permissions on
them, all of that.
And that's not our
problem right now, right?
We don't have that many files,
so I think our problem is that
these files are extremely large.
So that probably means
that these files
have lots and lots of blocks.
And for each block we
have to remember
where it is, right?
So that's how I anticipate
that this name node is
suffering right now.
There's so many logical
blocks and it needs to,
for every logical
block, remember
the physical locations of it.
All right, so I think that
what we want to do is
we want to reduce the number
of blocks to reduce how much
the name node needs to remember.
I mean, short of deleting data,
the way we can have
fewer blocks is
to have bigger blocks, right?
So let's say we like
double the block size.
Then we would have
half as many blocks
in this situation and
then the name node
would only need
half as much memory
to keep track of
all this state, right?
I had to be a little
careful and say
that these were large
files because a lot
of HDFS clusters I've seen
have a lot of small files,
and the small files are
smaller than one block.
Or maybe like one block is like
128 megabytes and then the
file is like 1 megabyte.
So then like the block size
kind of becomes irrelevant,
it's just how many
files you have.
But in this case, we
have large files,
so the block size is
what is getting us here.
Do people have questions about
that or Yeah, right here.
Oh, what is it when it's
becoming a bottle enneck? Right?
So I, I guess,
yeah, it's kind of an analogy,
but it's a term people use
a lot in systems, right?
So let's say that
I'm reading a file and then
like analyzing it, right?
I'm using multiple
resources there.
I'm using like the
disk and also the CPU.
And usually the resources of
the machine are not perfectly
proportional, right?
It's usually that my disc
is like really slow and then
my CPU is not very
fully utilized.
So what I'd say then is that my
My disk is a bottleneck, right?
Because even if I
had a faster CP,
it wouldn't matter
because the data
flowing from the
disk is too slow.
And so what I was
referring to here is you
could some clusters
would be less likely,
but you could
imagine a situation
where the name node is
keeping up just fine,
but the data nodes are
under too heavy load.
And then in that case we need to
help out the data
nodes in systems,
you want to find out what
the limiting factors
and improve that.
That makes sense.
Thanks. Yeah, right here.
How would I help if there's
a lot of small files?
Yeah, that would be
a harder problem
if there's a lot
of small files U,
you know, I guess
like the solution
would be to have
more large files.
And so that would
probably be very
dependent on what
the application
is doing on top of it, right?
So what are some things
that run on top of HDFS?
I mean, Map reduce
runs on top of HDFS,
H base runs on top of HDFS.
And so I'd have to start
learning more about
Map Reduce or HBase and
figure out how to tune them.
So for example, when I
run a map reduced job,
every reducer produces
its own file, right?
And so maybe I
might start running
my map reduced jobs and
I have fewer reducers.
I mean, that creates
its own problem,
but it would at least
solve this problem, right?
So I think that would definitely
be a harder problem to solve.
And that means it's
a great question,
but it's trickier.
Yeah, right here.
Should you go over
a question 13?
It deponent, yeah. Sure, sure.
So let's take a look
at question 13.
Okay, so remember we
have all these different
topics, right?
But sometimes a topic might
be very high volume and if
a topic is handled by a
single replica or a replica,
like a leader replica and it's
followers and it might
not be able to keep up.
So what we've done is
that we already have
these separate topics which
each have their own name.
And then we might say, oh,
for this topic
we're going to have
a few different
partitions on it and
each partition is
going to be handled
by a different set of replicas,
right? And so we did that.
Now that's straight, right?
That can kind of solve
our scalability problem.
But there are times when we
want certain messages
that are related to each
other to go in the
same partition
because there's a consumer
somewhere reading
that partition.
And maybe for it to do
the analysis correctly,
maybe it's like a streaming
group by or whatever,
it needs to see all the messages
with the same same key.
Right? So the way we do
it is at first, I mean,
if it's a different topic,
it's just completely different.
And then after that we
need to figure out,
well, what partition
will it go to?
And the way it does
it is it hashes
the key and then it will take
the key modular number
of partitions, right?
So if I model Ts and
it's like five and then
I have two partitions,
the five mod two as one.
So we go to partition one.
So really what I'm
looking for is,
do I have any cases where it's
the same topic and the same key?
And I don't, so I
really can't guarantee
anything about
messages being co,
located with each other.
Right? Then you asked
the other question,
which is, what does
it mean for something
to be item potent?
Item potent refers to
operations, right?
So oftentimes the messages
we're recording
are some kind of,
they could be represented
as an operation, right?
Either like, oh, there's
this new thing that
should be added or something
that should be updated.
Something like that.
Idea of item potent
means that if
we somehow have
duplicates, that's okay.
Because doing
something one time or
doing something n times where
n is greater than one would have
the same same result, right?
And so that was important
to us because we
wanted to have exactly
one semantics, right?
If I'm trying to
send a message once,
it's trying to get processed
exactly once on the other end.
So we first said
like, well, hey,
if we only have it
impotent operations,
then it's fine if
we have duplicates.
Right? Duplicates
come because we have
to retry when
things fail. Right?
And then we talked about
some other ways
that you could take
something that's Itempontent
and make it it impotent.
Judge, does that
answer the question?
Yeah.
Great question. Yeah. If anybody
has any follow up on
that or other questions.
Yeah. Right here we
see small files like Oh, sure.
So, kind of going
back to question 11.
So if we took that those
large files and we
split them into
many small files,
that will actually be even
worse for the name node.
P is the name node,
needs to remember
a little bit of information
about every possible file,
so that would create
more meta data.
We are, we only get one
name node, so we can't.
So yeah, maybe we'll have
more data nodes or maybe not.
But the bottleneck
is the name node.
We can't create more
name nodes, right?
That's just like
the design, right?
And that was actually, you know,
HDFS was inspired by
the Google file system.
The Google file system
had the same problem.
And they replaced the
Google file system
with the classes file system,
which doesn't have that
limitation of one name node.
In open source world,
I think we haven't got
in there yet, right?
They are here.
So in general, BreaS's
better to have large
files. Not many files.
Many small files, yes.
In HDFS you want to have
a few very large files. That's
what it's designed for.
Following that, I remember
I think it was Spark.
Generally, one large file
might internally
use small files.
Multi park files,
they use each worker.
Mm, mm hmm. I guess why
was that happening?
Is better. Oh, yeah, sure.
So I think you're saying that
sometimes we would run
a Spark job and then
we'd have like a lot of
little files created, right?
And that is not to make
it better for HDFS,
but to make it better
for Spark, right?
Because in Spark
they're trying to
distribute this work, right?
And so if I have an RDD, right,
there's a number
of partitions for
it and each partition of
an RDD runs as its
own task, right?
So if I have ten partitions,
then I can run on ten tasks,
which means I can use ten CPUs
somewhere throughout
my cluster, right?
So they will try to distribute
the work like that.
And then, uh, I want each
of those tasks be able,
run indepenpendently
of each other.
Which means that I can't
have two different tasks
writing to the same file.
That's why I might get
a lot of small files.
Now I guess even
with Spark though,
there's like an overhead to
starting too many tasks.
It takes a while
for it to start up,
so you don't necessarily
want to have
to small partitions
there either,
but Spark probably
is happier to have
smaller files than HDFS
is happy to have, right?
Yeah, that's a good question.
Yeah, right back here.
Question seven from this one?
Yeah, let's take a look
at question seven.
All right? This one right here,
which format is unlike the
other three in use cases?
I'm sorry, what did
you say? Oh, great.
Yeah, so what are each of these?
Okay, so the history
here is that
Dugal first developed
protocol buffers
and that was used for GRPC
is among other things.
And sometimes they
would get huge.
I think they would sometimes
have like protocol buffers
with like thousands
of fields in them.
And a bad way to do analysis
would be to have like
a big array of protocol buffers.
Because as you'd be reading
over each of those,
you would be doing a bunch
of random disco, right?
So at Dugal, what they
developed instead
was this format
called Tl Myo, right?
And Columbo they published
about in a paper called Dremel.
So Dremel was this in house
SQL engine they built.
That was really kind of
eating into a lot of
the use cases that map produce
had done and so they
published about that.
And then based on Tomyo,
there were two other systems
that were inspired, right,
Based on that paper I think
linked in and maybe Cloudera.
A couple of companies
read that like, well,
let's make an open source
version of Colum Io,
which they called Parke,
which is I think,
the one on here that maybe
we're most familiar with.
And then internally in Google,
they added some more
features to column
O later on like
dictionary entoding
or run length tooting.
And so they internally replaced
column with capacitor, right?
So kind of u, column Io is kind
of like logical parent
of capacitor and parte.
And then proto buff was just for
a completely different use case,
so I would say proto buff
is the one that doesn't fit
in with other ones. Yeah,
thank you for asking.
Yeah, over here proof.
Well, I think that so I
guess when we have proto
buff like we compile it and
then we get some maybe
pipeline classes
or bus classes or whatever,
and we actually have
a way of taking
some data and converting
it to bytes, right?
So you could imagine I had
a big table of data and I could
convert every row into
a protocol buffer,
and then I could
have a big array
of bytes for each of my rows.
That would actually
be a fine thing
to do if I wanted to like loop
over if I wanted to access
an entire row at a time.
But that'd be a terrible
idea if I wanted
to pull out one field
from each of them.
Because all the values
in the same column would
not be next to each
other on desk, Right?
What you said is true, right?
Protocol buffers, I have
a way to find a schema,
but it also defines a
byte format for data.
And that byte format
is row oriented.
It's not column oriented.
Yep.
Yeah, Great question.
Yeah, all the questions people
have. Yeah, right here.
Yeah, let's start
to the practice one
and number 20. All right?
I keep losing those papers,
I should just keep it over here.
Okay, great. So they're
considering two ways to produce,
train, and test data in Spark.
So random split.
Random split with a seed.
And the answer,
very surprisingly,
is that neither way is
really deterministic.
And the reason why is that
these data frames, right,
they're based on RDDs,
which have a bunch of
partitions, right?
And when they're doing
the train test split,
they don't want to have to
shuffle the data around.
So they're doing the
train test split on
each partition
independently, right?
So what I'll say is that if we
run it twice and we have
the same number of
partitions each time,
the same partitioning
and we have the seed,
then it would be deterministic,
but we're not guaranteed
that we're going to have
the same number of
partitions each time, right?
So Spark is trying to be smart
about figuring out how many
partitions do you have.
So maybe they'll look at like
how many CPUs do we
have in our cluster,
how much memory do we
have, All of these things.
And so one of the weird
things that could happen
is that you have this
big spark cluster,
you like run all this
and then, I don't know,
maybe some machines
go offline or
whatever and it has
a different worker
count and you rerun it
and it partitions it differently
and then it does the train test
split on each partition
and all of a sudden you
have different results.
Right? And so.
It's frustrating because if
you do it twice in a row,
like probably it's the same,
but it's a little misleading.
So the takeaway here is that
when you're doing this stuff
like save your train and test
data like somewhere else.
And then the way you
get determinism is
you always throw back
to those same files.
And we actually saw something
similar for big query as well.
Big query is not doing
this deterministically,
kind of oddly,
it just seems like
something basic that
all these systems
should prioritize.
Even if it's like if
somebody's passing a seed,
they care about it probably
more than performance, right?
So they should do it
deterministically, but they don't.
Well, I think that if you have
the same partition
and the same seed,
it will do that split the same.
But when I do it twice, maybe
at first I did with like
four partitions and now again
there's like five partitions.
So that's why I can't guarantee
it would be running
the same way.
Yeah, Excellent point.
That's like a gotcha, right?
That you'll have to watch for
when you're programming, right?
Yeah. I saw a hand up over here.
Is it guaranteed
that if you have
the same number of partition,
the data is actually
in the same fashion?
Oh, you're saying?
Oh, you're saying if you have
the same number of partitions,
will Rowan let's add two
partitions and nine rows.
Is it going to be like a 5.4,
then a four, then a five?
Your yeah, you had four to
two. Yeah, back to four.
Really guarantee
the original data
is sort of the same way in
the first four partitions
as it is in the second and
therefore will know
how to analyst.
Yeah, I think
that's hard to say.
I'm not sure. Right, Because
Yeah. But I see
what you're saying.
Right. If the partitions
are the same,
like it could potentially
change or maybe it doesn't.
And so I've tried
to pen down what they're
doing and there's
these long articles about it
and by good sources
and there's like all
this detailed nuance.
And then like most
recent articles will say
like Spark has gotten better
about this but not
completely solving and like,
well, it's either you do
it or you don't, right?
I mean, kind of if it's
better but it doesn't fix it,
then it's just like it
is more misleading.
So I think that, and who knows,
maybe it's a moving target too.
I think the takeaway
is that they don't
really give you the
guarantee you want.
And so I don't
know how close to that
guarantee they give you.
Right.
So aside from this, yeah.
Is it deterministic,
how smart partitions,
the data given the number
of partitions that you set?
I don't know.
That's what you're asking.
I don't know if
it's deterministic.
And that might be something that
maybe it used to not
be and maybe it is.
I don't know if people
mean when they say
it's gotten better.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Lots
of interesting things,
but like the main
takeaway is that
don't depend on it. All right.
Another question back.
What are the assumptions
about, about partition size?
Or
they might change
the partition size, right? Yeah.
So I think the
question is like, I
guess what guarantees
do you have?
And if there are guarantees,
I don't know what they are, so I
want to assume there
are any guarantees.
Yeah, I hand up question.
Yeah. Let's take a look
at question 18. Cool.
Numbers are being read into
a topic that is read by
a streaming Spp query
is adding the numbers
and showing the output.
The numbers have been
produced so far,
103.4 and then the latest
output is 27, okay?
So what semantics does
the system as a whole
seem to be providing?
Well, definitely
not exactly once.
I mean, we would have got 107,
doesn't seem like at
most once, right?
Doesn't seem like
anything got drop.
It seems like some
of these things
are being counted twice, right?
We're doing some double counting
going on. Does that make sense?
Yeah. Good question. Yeah. And I
saw another hand up over here.
Yeah, question 20. It's not a
bad, right?
Yeah, this does
not guarantee it.
Right? And the takeaway I
want people to have for
both Spark and Big Query is
not kind of like what the
technical quirks of what
they're doing right now,
which is probably
going to change
like maybe in the
next year, right?
The takeaway is that unless they
explicitly give you a
strong end guarantee,
like we have fixed this, then
what I want you to do is
I want you to save your
data somewhere else.
All right? That's
the main takeaway.
That is like we
practically apply, right?
Yeah, Yeah, Yeah.
Thank you for
following up on that.
Yeah. Other questions people
have?
Yeah, go ahead.
I think it was number four.
Yeah. Let's head back to the
practice test right here.
So is this one right here?
Yeah.
Okay. So if you
have lots of Ram,
which caching level would
generally be fastest?
Okay, so there's different
places we can keep the data.
When it's cache, it can
either be memory or on desk,
and then there's different
formats our data can be in.
Right, the instruction
that the CPU.
Can do.
Expect the data to be in
a specific format, right?
Like 32 is trying to
take exactly four bytes.
Ideally it's going
to be like aligned,
right, to operate on it.
And that format that
the CPU has is not
necessarily the densest
expression of the data, right?
Like maybe if I have a
small integer in my N 32,
why not use a fewer
number of bytes like
protopops do or Spark
Serialization does, right?
So these two are
serialized, right?
These two are
putting the data in
a format where it's time of
using less space but
the CPU cannot directly
operate on them.
That makes a lot of sense
for disc only, right?
Because disc IO is slow, right?
So it's probably worthwhile
to use a little bit of
CPU to kind of
shrink down the data before
we write it to desk.
These two are kind
of interesting
because they're both in memory.
And this one will be
bigger than this one because
this one is not serialized.
But if I'm doing computation I
can just directly do it
without transforming the data.
That would be faster, right?
So I have lots of Ram,
so why not use
that extra Ram to do what
will be faster for me?
Does that make sense?
Yeah, great question.
Yeah, all the questions,
people have a distinction.
Why, why you versus Oh, sure.
So why would I use B versus C?
Well, drawing to disk
is very slow, right?
So kind of, you know,
I might remember that
both B and C serialize.
I guess they just didn't put
serialization in C's name
for whatever reason,
and so I've serialized it.
And then the question is,
well, do I keep it in memory?
If I have enough memory,
that sounds nice.
If I'm short on
memory, then let's
put it to disc instead, right?
Putting it to disc instead,
it is still probably better
than like, I don't know,
having HTFS file somewhere else
that they're starting to
require remote access.
Right. Does anybody remember?
So these were the three
levels I wanted to remember.
And then there was
like actually three
more levels as well in
addition to these that I
could reasonably ask
questions about.
What does remember with
all their three were.
Yeah, right here.
Oh, that's true too.
So I think that we did
talk about the level of
12.3 CPU caches early
in the semester,
so that's a little bit
orthogonal to that, right?
So we talked about in the
cache hierarchy, right, a CPU,
it takes a long time for it
to access data from Ram,
so it would have a
very small cache, L,
one that's kind of fast
and close to the core,
that'll do a little
bit farther away.
So that's true,
right? There's also
something that kind
of looked like that,
but was another idea that we
had for the spark caching.
Anybody remember what that
was? Yeah, right here.
Excellent, right, so
each one of these had
a version where it was
two times replication.
So just say under sore
two after each of these.
And that would do
exactly the same thing,
but instead of keeping
it on one spark worker,
it would be on two
spark workers.
What would be some
advantages of having
it on multiple spark workers?
I mean, the downside is that
we're using more space,
but why might we
get some benefit
out of using that additional
space? Yeah, right here.
Maybe more concurrency, right?
Or I guess maybe
you're saying like,
hey, maybe I want to do different
tasks on the same data?
Yeah, I think that's
true. I hadn't
mentioned that this semester,
but that makes sense.
Yeah.
Yeah. Other thoughts?
Yeah, right here.
Safer? Yeah. Safer.
Chase, data gets lost.
I mean, as cash data
can always redo it,
but that might slow
things down a lot, right?
You know, this might
be at the end of
a very long RDD chain, right?
And so if I lose that,
maybe all of a
sudden it takes like
multiple minutes to recover
that data, so Absolutely Right.
I'm safer in case I just lost.
And then there was
one other reason that
I had mentioned this semester.
Yeah, go ahead, put it
closely data that you're
working. Oh, sure.
You're saying that if I
have kind of two choices,
maybe lets me paired up with
other data like maybe if
I was doing a joint
or something,
I hadn't thought about
that. But that seems true.
Yeah. So I guess people are,
this is kind of interesting me,
people are coming up with lots
of reasons I hadn't
thought about.
Like the main one I
was thinking about
was in terms of load
balance, right?
Different workers have
different amounts of load.
And when I'm running
a task, I want to
run the task where
the data is cached.
And if I have two choices of
where to run that
task instead of one,
then I can better balance
load across, across the cluster.
Yeah, Well, it ended
up being a pretty
interesting a lot
drawing on there. Right.
All right. Cool. Yeah.
What else do people
have? Yeah, right here.
Yeah. Another one. On this one.
Oh, you're saying
could they have three?
That would make a lot of
sense, but they just don't.
It's like and then, yeah,
to me it would make
sense to say like here's
the level and here's the
number of replications.
But they don't, they're
just like they baked it in.
And they go to go beyond two.
Why? I have no idea.
All right. Yeah, Yeah.
All of questions people
have. Yeah, over here.
Yeah, let's do three, right?
So you're using Spark to
join two large tables that
are roughly equal in size.
We have a bunch of
workers involved.
Which joint algorithm
would you pack?
Right?
So I'm going to
say that these are
about size, whatever that means.
Let's just do a back of
the envelope calculation.
A large number of workers,
let's say they are
like M workers.
All right? So when I do a
shuffle, sort, merge, join.
What I'm trying to do is hash,
partitioning both tables at
the same time on whatever
key it is I'm using to join.
And so I can have
pairs of partitions.
That are going to
match with each other.
I want to bring those
pairs of partitions
next to each other
on the same machine.
And so that basically
means that both of
these tables are going to
go over the network, right?
So this will be two of network.
All right, so it's
not great to send
two large tables completely
over the network. But
what will this one do?
The broadcast hash join
finds the smaller table,
which is not super helpful
here because they're
both of size.
And it sends that smaller table
to every worker that's involved.
Right, So this one
would be M times T of
N. Right,
So the broadcast hash join
would be terrible for
this scenario where
the broadcast
hash join works really well.
Is if I have like a giant table
that I don't want to
send over the network.
And then the other
table is so tiny,
I'm happy to send it
to every single worker
and have them just
keep it in memory.
Right.
So broadcast hash in
high table skew and the
smaller table fits in memory.
Yeah. Any follow ups on
that one? All right, cool.
I saw a hand up here in
the front row, right?
Or you had a hand up?
Yeah. Okay, great.
It was a question. 21? Yeah,
this example was a question.
So hosts versus host 20 VM?
Yeah. So I guess we did 21 here.
So you're saying it
must be 21 on the Yeah.
Uh huh. What kind of
host are we to play?
Our RVMs this semester and
we did multi tenant host.
Right. So a tenant is just
like a customer who is
who is paying the con
provider and then
the host is the actual
physical machine
where they're running this work.
And so if you are
asultenant host,
that means that you
would be paying for
this entire machine
just for you.
Right? And that'd be
very expensive, right?
Kind of the only
reason you do that,
if you're like very paranoid
about security and maybe like,
you know, Department of
Defense or something,
then yeah, they would
definitely do that.
But like, students
would never do it.
Most normal companies would
not do it maybe. Right.
Yeah. So that makes
sense. So follow up.
Yeah. So in a multitest
would never get preempted.
Right. Is that a
different type of host?
Oh, okay. So, so I
guess preempted, right?
We did talk about
preemption this semester.
We talked about preemption
in terms of big query.
Preemption means that they
can give you resources and
then like snatch it back. Right?
And so that's a
different topic, right?
So I think that when
you deploy a VM, right,
you can deploy like a VM
on demand and then they wouldn't
normally take it away
from you, right?
Or you could pay a reduced price
for what is called
a spot instance.
So for a spot instance,
like the price is like
fluctuating throughout the day,
kind of depending on
their overall load.
And so you might say like, oh,
this is the price I'm
building to pay for.
And then when it
gets cheap enough,
you would run and then
we actually need it
for somebody else and
they would kick you off.
Right. So that would
be another concept.
So we don't have spot, we
didn't use spot
instances this semester,
but spot instances would
also be a multi tenant? Yep.
Yeah. Good question. Yeah,
there are questions people
have. Yeah. All
right. Back here?
Yeah, it's 217 on the exam.
All right, so the planet
algorithm, right?
So that was that paper that
Google published and then they
implemented it in Spark, right?
To train decision trees.
And the idea of planet
is that sometimes
the data that we're
using to train our decision tree
is so big that we
don't want to like
shuffle it all over the
network every time, right?
So they actually had
this hybrid system.
They had one way
to select a node split that
doesn't move the data around.
And then as we're
building the tree, right,
as we get farther and
farther down in the tree,
each node has fewer and
fewer rows of data.
And eventually
they realize that,
oh, there's not that
many rows of data.
Let's just bring all the rows
together in memory
on the same machine.
And then keep, you know,
recursing until we finish
training it, right?
So they have these two
kinds of jobs, right?
So this is talking about
the smaller job, right?
So the data has gone
small enough that we can
run like within that node,
there's few enough rows
we can finish in memory.
And so what we have to do
is we have to pull, right?
We have our big
decision tree, right?
And we have different nodes, and
some of these nodes are small,
and those nodes
each have some rows
associated with them, right?
So we have to pull
all the rows for
the same decision tree node on
the same physical machine to
finish running the
algorithm, right?
And that's what hash
partitioning does.
Hash partitioning pulls
together related data, right?
And so if we want to finish
training the decision tree,
we have to pull
together all the rows
that belong to the same
node and that decision
tree so we can run the algorithm
in memory there, right?
So our answer would be
this one right here.
Does that makes sense?
Excellent.
That was one of the
trickier algorithms
we looked at this semester.
So yeah, right here.
Oh, excellent,
Yeah. Okay, great.
So O L stands for online,
P stands for processing.
And so the two letters I
really care about
are transactions,
and then this one is Analytics
for transaction
processing workload.
I mean, transactions also means
this other thing that is
related to concurrency.
But in this case,
transaction processing
just means like maybe
like I insert a row,
delete a row, look up a row.
Kind of like, you know,
maybe a shopping
card or any kind of
like online web application
would be transaction processing.
And the format they're
probably going to
be using for that
on disk is going to
be a row oriented
format because I'm
often accessing a whole
row at the same time.
Analytics, in contrast, we're
often doing things like
adding all the
numbers in a column
or accessing a whole
column at a time.
So we'd want to column
oriented format, right?
So my sequel was
an LTP one, right?
So I'm good at inserting rows.
Removing rows, it
would be slow if
you wanted to take
the average of a column
or something like that.
At least if you have a lot
of data, it would be slow.
If data is small
China, it doesn't
matter what you use, right?
So what somebody might do
is they might be using
my transaction processing for
some web application, right?
But then when they
want to analyze,
they might have some extract,
transform and load job
that extracts it out of
that my squeal and then loads it
into maybe some
part files in HDFS.
So you could do your analytics
someplace else? Yeah.
Excellent question.
Yeah. Any follow ups on that
while we're talking about
analytics versus
transaction processing?
Yeah. Or any questions about
anything? Yeah, right here.
Odile Spark.
Oh, oh,
oh, so you said would
Spark L be what?
Spark loads a CSV file.
Possession file. Oh, sure.
Oh, okay. I think it raises
a good point, right?
You're saying like
Spark, first off,
Spark is designed for analytics,
So what if Spark is
loading a CSV file, right?
Because the CSV file is
actually bro oriented,
right? So it can do that.
And so what I'll say is that
analytics refers to the kinds
of work we're trying
to do, right?
And some systems, right,
like Park are optimized
for analytics.
And then other
things like my QL or
CSV files are not
optimized for analytics.
And so the situation
you're describing,
what I say is that you're
using an analytics,
you're using analytics
processing on data
that is not optimized
for analytics, right?
You could do analytics on my QL.
It's just not efficient if
you have a lot of data
that makes sense.
But like analytics refers
to what were the kind of
work we're trying to do,
not necessarily
the system, right?
I can do overlap work
on an OLTP database.
It's just not a
good idea, right?
Yeah. Yeah. Thank
you for clarifying.
Thanks for bringing back
the point about CSP's too.
Yeah, Yeah. What
else do people have?
Yeah, Right here.
Oh, yeah. Go ahead.
Yeah. Yes. You haven't had
doesn't have any questions
yet. Read park file?
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
You're saying you're using
spar here, Reading park file.
That's all like
analytics. What about oh,
oh, let me just clarify here.
Right. So this question
is asking about my Q,
which is, you know,
this is a Q dba for OLTP, right?
Like the language
is suitable for
both OLTP and Olap,
right?
So Sql, right?
Just generally, it's
just a language, right?
And some questions
you might ask might
be more role oriented.
Some questions you
might ask might be
more Tlm oriented, right?
And then any database engine
that interprets Quel can kind
of be fast at one
kind of query and
slow at the other or
vice versa, Right?
Does that makes
sense? Yeah, sorry,
I see where the
confusion came from.
Yeah, that's a great
clarification. All right.
So I think we're at time
but I can sit around
for a few minutes if people
want to come up
and ask questions.
Otherwise, good luck with
the final stretch of study
and with our exam
and all your exams.