Here today. Welcome to
CS 544 and throw to
Big Data Systems.
I'm really excited to teach
at this semester because
it's our first official
offering of the course.
Last spring we did a trial run.
I think it went pretty well.
You know, some things
we're we fighting,
but now it's approved with
a real course number.
And so I'm excited to
do a first official run
of the course this semester.
I'm going to do some
introductions of the course of
myself td get a sense of
who's taking the course,
talk about some
logistical things today,
and then we will
have some time to
dig into some
technical topics too.
My name's Tyler Carroza Hard.
I'm actually a longtime badger.
I was undergrad here myself,
maybe taking some of the same
courses you all are taking.
My E mail is on the screen.
I just drove by my first name.
You just call me
Tyler, and I use
male pronouns prior to teaching.
I worked with a variety of
companies like Google, Facebook,
Microsoft, and more recently
with some smaller companies,
Entry and Bow Plan.
Happy to talk about that
if anybody's interested.
Also on the side,
I'm very interested
in open source and
particularly I'm working on a
project called Open Lambda.
That's open source
cloud platform
where people can just write
little functions that
will run in response
to events and is
highly scalable.
If you're interested in
Open Source or that
project in general,
happy to chat about that.
Let me get a quick
sense of you all.
Do we have any freshmen taking
the course of semester?
What about sophomores?
Juniors and seniors.
So pretty senior heavy too.
Very similar to the
morning section.
And what about grad students?
Do we have any grad students
taking the course of semester?
Well, a lot of you
actually welcome.
Right. I think, you know,
the course makes
sense at all levels.
I think we're coming
from a variety
of different backgrounds.
320 is probably the main
path end of this course,
but 400 is also a path.
And I know some of you
have already gone on and
maybe have taken some
other upper level courses.
Even though, of course,
that's not expected.
And I'm going to assume
that you've taken
just something like 320 or 400.
But how many have taken the
operating system course
537. So a few of you.
What about the
database course 564,
bit less, and has
anybody taken 640?
The networking course. So
just a handful of you.
Great. So it'll be awesome
if you can all go fill
this form today or if you
join the course slate.
As soon as you join
the course fill that,
there's a link on it
from the website too,
that will help me get
some statistics on this.
And also when I'm
evaluating the course,
I want to make sure
that even if a lot of
you have taken these upper
level courses that are related,
I really want to gear
the course towards
people who have just
taken 320 or 400, right?
So it will help me kind
of see where people are
and make sure I'm setting the
difficulty appropriately.
Um, if you fill that,
that also accounts
for extra credit,
so please be sure to do that.
Here are some of those other
courses and how they fit in.
The main computer science track
that people take is in Java.
That's a CS 200, 300, 400.
And there's a variety of courses
that people can take after that.
Some of the courses
are maybe what
I might call systems courses.
There's a systems track in
parallel with that,
with 252.3 54.
After you've taken
all of those five,
there's a bunch of
courses you can take like
databases and operating systems.
When we were looking at
big data systems courses
at other universities,
a lot of them would
have prerequisites on
courses like databases
or operating systems.
And of course, that
starts to become
a very nasty prec chain.
You have to take a lot of
courses to be involved,
and I think the
things we're learning
are very applicable
to data scientists.
So we wanted to design it
so people could take 22320,
which is the Python track
of the data science major,
and then directly take 544.
Now I think that
one thing that that
means is that the first third of
this course has a lot of
overlap with some of these
other upper level CS courses.
And what I saw last semester
is that some of those people
coming from the CS side who have
taken those upper level courses,
maybe got a little bit
complacent at the
beginning because
it felt easy and felt familiar.
And then when we started doing
new stuff and it
was kind of a jolt.
So just don't get lulled into
complacency based on the
first third of the semester.
If you've seen some of
these things before,
I know there are a lot
of grad students here.
So I think that the grad big
data systems that we're in,
Intro Big Data Systems.
The difference is that
at the grad level,
you're maybe reading research
about research papers about
some of these systems.
Maybe you're coming
up with novel
ideas to build new systems.
Our main focus here is how to be
effective users of
big data systems.
You aren't going to be
building much like brand
new systems from scratch or
reading research papers.
They're going to
be very hands on
getting practice with a lot
of these different tools.
You know, I think
everybody coming out of
the 320 side is going to be
very comfortable on Python.
Those of you who haven't seen
Python before that are
coming from the CS side,
here are a couple of books in
Python is fairly introductory,
it's a quick read.
If you want to just get a
flavor of the language,
I recommend that fluent Python
is more advanced Python book.
And honestly, I think
even if you're very
comfortable with Python,
have used a lot.
If you read through that, I
can guarantee there's going
be some interesting things
you'll learn there as well.
I know I certainly learned
a lot from reading through that.
So this is big data systems,
but what are systems in general?
We're all programmers, but
we write different
kinds of code.
One kind of code we might
write is for analysis.
Maybe I'll give you a dataset
and ask you some
questions about it.
And then you write some
code that probably runs
once and produces some
numbers and some plots.
That's one kind of programming.
Applications Programming has
a bit of a different flavor.
You can imagine if I have
like a website where I have
a shopping card and I'm
recommending things to people.
That's a program that's running
really indefinitely, right?
So kind of a different
kind of programming style.
And you might use different
languages for that.
But both of these analysis and
applications are
based on systems.
And what systems do is they
help us manage resources.
So you could imagine
that if I want
to do some analysis
of a CSV file,
well, that CSV file is on
a hard drive somewhere and coded
as a bunch of ones and zeros.
What a pain to deal with that
thanks to an operating system,
one kind of system, we can read
that file in more easily, right?
So some of you will go on and
you're going to be
building new systems.
But even if you don't learning
how systems work
is going to make
you a better
programmer no matter
what kind of programming
you're using,
you're doing.
Because you'll be able to
learn how to use these systems
efficiently and make good
use of your resources.
Okay, so what is a
big data system?
I mean, it's kind of
a arbitrary threshold
here and maybe people might feel
differently about
it over overtime.
The way I think of it is
that I have my laptop
here and there's some basic
things I can do with it.
And when I'm kind of pushing
beyond the limits of what I
could do on just one computer
with regular hardware,
I'm going to call that
a big data system.
So for example, if I have to
have specialized
hardware like GPUs,
that we can think of that
as a big data system.
Or the more common taste is
maybe I need a whole cluster of
machines working together
on the same problem.
That would be a big data system.
Here's an overview
of the things that
I want you to learn
this semester.
Number one is we have to be
able to deploy these systems.
That means, you
know, installing it,
dotting up and running, getting
all the different computers,
talking to each other.
That's actually harder
than you might think.
And it's important role many
of you will have on jobs
some day After you did these
systems up and running,
how do you get data
into them, right?
That can be a lot
of work as well.
Okay, once we're up and running,
we have some data there,
we might want to do
things like analyze
the data or do machine
learning with it.
So there's the next couple
learning objectives.
Of course, we want to do
all this efficiently.
So we want to measure
how many resources
we're using to
solve our problems.
And then find ways
to optimize and
reduce how many
resources we need.
Finally, a lot of
this has evolved.
It might be in the past that
you would buy a bunch of
computers or your company would
and you'd run their software.
Are there now it's more
common that you might
be running these
things in the cloud.
And I want to talk about
how we use Cloud services
effectively and think about
the pricing for them.
That's the whole semester.
Today, I just have a
few more narrow goes.
First, I want to talk about the
logistics and policies
for the course.
And then on the technical side,
I want to talk about
different kinds of
hardware resources we're going
to be managing this semester.
And I want to talk about
how we can either scale up,
which means buying more
expensive machines,
or scale out by buying
clusters of machines.
Then finally, we're going
to talk a bit about
how does your code
actually run on a CPU?
Some of you might have
seen some of these before,
but I want to make sure we're
all on the same page about what
actually happens when you're
trying to run a program.
All right, so there's
three main sites that we're
going to use this semester.
One of them is Canvas.
And I think most courses
use Canvas in some ways.
How many of you got my
announcement already?
I've been doing announcements
on Canvas. That's awesome.
Make sure that if you're not
a regular Canvas checker,
there's a way to
turn on an option
that'll e mail you whenever
there's a Canvas announcement.
This is a centralized
place where I do
all just broadcast
messaging to everybody.
Is if people join the
course late or something,
they can just jump on and
catch up on everything.
Make sure you're getting
those messages there.
Other things I use
Canvas for are quizzes.
We're have those weekly
sync with Top Hat.
I'm going to give you
summaries of your grades
here and we'll have some
office hours over Zoom.
That's one site that you
have to be aware of.
The most important site though,
is this public facing site
that I've shared with you
All this shows the overview
of the course schedule
and resources per day.
For example, you can come
here and you can see
this is the syllabus you're
supposed to read today.
Here, the slides I've posted.
And I'm trying something
new this semester,
which is giving you
all flash cards to
just memorize some of
the basic vocabulary and
other basic ideas that are
related to the course.
I have slides up
from last semester,
but I'm going to be
tweaking those so you
can see if I've
already updated it.
This is just if you
want to peek ahead and
did a flavor of what we're
doing in the course.
The syllabus is here. Please
make sure you read that.
I have a page for getting help.
There's lots of ways
you can get help.
If you aren't sure where,
jump on this page and try to
see what is a good fit for you.
Questions of general interest
are a good fit for Piazza.
We're going to be
monitoring that.
Just make sure you don't
post more than five lines of
code at a time
because then people
are going to start
cheating off of you.
I'm going to be assigning
you each an E mail contact.
That'll be one of the
TA's in the course.
And then there's
other details about
office hours and accommodations.
Below we have a bunch of
resources such as datasets,
office hour schedule.
I'll often be posting
little snippets
of code on this
document as we go.
This one right here, I
already have open over here.
You can see that
I'm on jehubjethub,
has organizations
and repository.
My organization is 544 west.
This semester is Fall 23.
May be posting all
of the projects.
If you look at some of them now,
you can see that
they're just drafts.
So this is just to
get a flavor of it,
but it's going to evolve until
I remove those comments.
I'm also going to often
be doing examples in
Jupiter Notebooks,
I'm be posting that here
as well after lectures.
A lot of that code
I'm doing during
lecture can help you
on your projects.
There's old exams and stuff
like that here as well.
I mentioned that this
or has this repo,
the way we're going to be
working this semesters at this
or will also have a
repo for each of you,
for every project that you do.
That's all. You'll be
making submissions,
you're going to be
pushing your code to
private repos that
we have access to.
All right, so those are
the three big websites that
you should share about most,
some other tools that
we're using a semester to,
how have you used Top Hat
and of course before.
Awesome. So hopefully
that goes smoothly.
I already posted a
canvas announcement
about a little practice
question you can do.
I'd say 90% of it is just,
you know, participating
in some way.
I'll give you a little
bit more points
like if you actually
get it right,
but it shouldn't really
be high pressure.
It's just mostly are you showing
up and kind of
engaging in lecture.
There's always some technical
difficulties with that.
If you have a technical
difficulty with
top hat or there's
another reason you
can't true to lecture,
then we have some forms over
here ahead to these forms,
you can report a lecture mass.
And that's just on
the honor system.
If you only do it like
seven or eight times,
I'll just trust you.
If it starts to get
more than that,
we have to talk and maybe
think about is there a reason
why some obstacle to top
working or something like that.
But in general, if
it's something rare,
just fill that out and
I'll just trust you on it.
I already mentioned Piazza.
We'll always have somebody
monitoring Piazza.
Our goal is to respond to every
question within 24 hours.
If something is more specific to
just say your project
or your team,
then you'll have a TA
that you can contact.
I'll assign each of you a
point of contact as a TA.
Our goal in that case
is to respond in
less than two business
hours every semester.
I know some TA's get
behind because they're
busy, They're students too.
And so if that happens,
what you should do is you
should just see me on
the thread with them,
and I'll kind of nudge them
to keep up on their E mails.
One thing I'll ask
that you do not do is
not start a separate thread
with me and your TA.
Because then we end
up doing double work,
we end up adds it twice,
or maybe in an inconsistent way.
So for one topic, keep
everybody involved
on the same thread.
Don't have multiple
threads about
the same thing I already
mentioned. Hub classroom.
Hub will actually very
easily let you just
flip it to public.
Don't do that, because people
are going to start
cheating off of
you always leave it private,
which is the default.
We're also going to be
giving you feedback on
your code on Github classroom.
And then finally,
I mentioned these
flash cards that I'm posting,
these work with a
tool called Ki.
Has anybody used Aki before?
Anybody here? A few of
you. That's awesome.
What I love about Ki is
that as you're doing it,
they will, you'll say like,
oh, did I get it right or wrong?
And if I got it right,
how hard was it for me?
And then they'll space out
how long you see it again
based on how you've
been doing with
it on that iteration
in the past.
And what I found is that if
there's like easy stuff for me,
I'll do it right a few
times and all of a
sudden I'll be like,
I won't ask me again
for two months.
But the stuff that
I'm really stuck on,
he'll keep showing it to me
until, until I master it.
And, you know, I
know in education
they're trying to like,
well, how important is
just raw memorization?
I think it's not our end role,
but it is important
because if we're talking
about more complicated topics,
we have to have a
common vocabulary.
And so some of that
stuff, you should just
do it until you're
fluent with it.
Same thing, like
there's a bunch of
shell commands or Dr.
commands I'm going to be
teaching this semester.
You should just
memorize that stuff.
So then as you're
debugging later,
you're just trying to
comfortable in this environment.
So there's a certain just
memorization
everybody should do.
And I'm going to do this as
an experiment this semester.
I'm hoping that will help
people trying to get
that base more
quickly. All right.
Do people have any logistical
questions about
the course so far?
Anybody should
always feel free to
pop up a hand any time
if they have questions.
Yeah, right here. Oh yeah.
Where is the top hat password?
So that is 5440.
Top password is 5440.
I don't know if there's a way
to get around the password,
but this is also
linked on canvas.
Since it's linked on Canvas,
everybody at some point has to
go through Canvas
and click it here.
Otherwise, it won't associate
your top hat with your canvas.
So please do that at some point.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
All right, cool. I'm
going ahead here.
Let's talk about resources.
Systems are about
managing resources.
Resource is a very broad word
and it can mean lots
of different things.
In this course, I'm focus on
four big categories of
computing resources.
And those are compute,
memory, storage, and networking.
And I have all those
things in my laptop,
or any computer would
have these four things.
Let's look at some examples.
A CPU central processing unit is
the main form of compute
power we have nowadays.
For a lot of big data sets,
people actually use GPU's,
Graphics processing units,
originally built for graphics,
but also suitable for a lot
of scientific computing
and machine learning.
Memory is Ram.
Gp's are also a little
bit on that side too,
because GPU's will have
their own built in Ram.
And when you're programming
this environment,
you have to think
about is my data in
my regular system Ram
or is it in my GPU Ram?
We're going to use Ram to hold
the active data we're
currently working
with in our program.
Storage holds long
term data and there's
two main devices we're
going to think about
this semester.
There's hard disk drives,
HD HDDs, and solid
state drives, SSD's.
We're going to talk
more later on about
the performance
tradeoffs between
these and where they
each do well or poorly.
But at first Brush,
we could just say
that SSDs are faster.
And then finally we
have network resources.
In this case, I have
a nick which is
a network interface card or
you might say controller.
And I can plug an
either net cable in
there and I could connect
that to a separate switch.
And if I connect a bunch of
computers to that switch,
well they can start
talking to each other.
All right?
So I have all these
different kinds of hardware,
like all of these
are flash cards too.
So just like kind of remembering
what these terms are,
maybe you know if what CPU is,
but maybe you don't
know what a nick is.
If you do those flash cards,
you're going to
practice the ones
that you're less familiar with.
How many of you have ever opened
up a computer and peeked inside?
It's a great thing to do
if you ever did a chance.
This is a peek inside of
a server and it has those
four resources right here,
we can actually see
what it looks like.
There are some hard
drives at the top.
We have some CPU's down here.
Those tend to get
hot, so there's
a big fan on each of them.
Over here I have all
these green sticks of Ram
and here's my network interface
controller right here.
All right, so we have all
these resources and we
can use these resources
to solve problems.
But what happens is the problem
is around some dataset
that's growing and getting
bigger and bigger.
One problem I might run on
too is that it might take too
long to do my computation.
That's a problem.
Even worse, if I don't
have enough memory,
I might not be able
to run it at all.
It might just crash in that
situation, what can we do?
One thing we could do is
try to write more
efficient code.
Maybe I go take an
algorithms class like
577 and maybe come
up with an algorithm that
has better complexity.
Eventually you'll
hit the end of that
and maybe the data
is still too big,
so eventually you
just have to throw
more resources at it, right?
And so here I have a computer.
There's different ways I could
throw more resources at it.
One is within that
same computer,
I could buy better hardware.
Maybe I buy faster
CPUs or more memory.
That's called scaling up.
When I just have
like one machine
and I give it more
computing power.
The other thing we
might do is we might
just buy more machines
that maybe independently,
none of them is anything
special, but as a cluster,
I have a lot of cumulative
computing power.
Dugal really pushed
this approach and what
they realized early on is that
scaling up was often
expensive, right?
If you bought twice
as much memory,
maybe it costs even more
than twice as much,
the smaller amount of memory.
So it's very expensive
buying this fancy hardware,
but you could buy what you might
call just commodity hardware
that's available
to everybody off
the shelf and that's cheap.
But you can buy a lot
of it and still get
the same cumulative computing
power at a cheaper rate.
That's called scale out.
That's going to be
most of what we're
thinking about this semester.
All right, let's take
a look at each of
these four resources now in
a little bit more detail,
now that we've had an overview.
Some computers have one CPU,
some have multiple CPUs.
I see this one right
here has two CPUs on it.
But regardless of how
many CPUs I have,
they might each have multiple
cores on that same chap.
Each of those cores acts like
its own little CPU that
I can run a user's code.
Right, so between here
maybe I might look,
maybe who knows. Maybe
I have eight on each.
I might have 16 cores total.
So how do cores actually
run a user's code?
So what I'm showing up here
is four different processes,
123.4 a process is
a running program.
I put in parentheses the
name of the program.
So you could totally
imagine Process 1.4 Maybe I
started the same program
twice on different shells
or something like that.
Each of these processes
have some things in common.
They have some code
which is in Ram,
and then they have some data
that they're operating on.
And when you're executing code,
the first thing you
need to know is, well,
what line of code am I on,
or what instruction am I on?
So each of these processes
has a little red arrow by it,
and that's called an
instruction pointer.
That's telling me, here's
the machine code you're
currently executing.
Now, at any given time,
CPU core can be running
one of these processes.
And I have more processes
and I have CPU cores.
So the operating system
is a piece of software
that's going to step in.
And one of the things
that does is it decides,
okay, now it's your
turn to run on a core.
And when you're running
code, what does that mean?
Well, I have some
outcomes but also
the line of code I'm
executing on changes.
Right, I'm stepping forward,
that instruction pointer
to execute the code.
This point I have two
processes, 1.2 are running.
And then some other ones that
are ready they could run,
but I'm not running
them right now.
The operating system will decide
when we switch who
gets to be running.
So now maybe I'm running
these two for a bit.
So we can see that the
more cores we have,
the more things we
can run in parallel
across all of these
different processes.
Okay, so what does that
code actually look like?
Well, it's actually
a machine code.
Maybe some of you have
taken 354. No worries.
If not, you'll learn that
machine code is these ones and
zeros that different
combinations
specify different operations
like adding or maybe like
jumping to a specific place
in your code or
things like that.
What I've shown up here is
something called assembly code.
An assembly code is a very
close relationship to
that machine code.
It's not zeros and ones,
but I have different
instructions here that would get
translated to those zeros
and ones in machine code.
Right? So that's
what I have there
and very few programmers are
ever programming and something
like machine code or assembly.
So my question is,
how do we bridge that
gap between languages?
We commonly write
code in Python, Java,
or whatever, and
the machine code.
Right? And the answer
is that there's different
ways to bridge that gap.
And it'll vary depending on
what programming
language you're using.
Almost everything
we're going to be
doing this semester
is in Python.
But that doesn't mean
that all the systems
we're using were themselves
built in Python.
For example, the system will
probably use most
is called Spark.
Spark was written in a
language called Scala,
and Scala runs on
something called the
Java Virtual Machine.
And so one of the things
that you're going
to be seeing when we're
programming later is
you're writing your Python code
and then there's an error.
There's a big stack trace.
And you'll read through it
in that same stack trace,
there'll be some Python code,
there will be some Scala code,
and there'll be some Java code,
right? I don't know Scala.
But because I understand
how these pieces kind of
fit together and I can get
a general sense of it,
I can still debug a
bit based on that.
And so that's why I want to
understand how all these pieces
fit together and how
code actually runs.
Because even though we
aren't doing Java or Scala,
we're going to be
touching it a little bit
and being able to read those
error messages will help us.
Okay, so how do we
bridge that gap?
Let's say we wrote some high
level code, I don't know,
let's say it's like C or C,
and we want to run
that on the CPU,
which only understands
machine code.
One way we could do
that is we could feed
our program through another
program called a compiler.
And the compiler would translate
that high level code down to
something that the
machine understands
and that could be run on a CPU.
All right, that's the first
approach, this compilation,
another approach that we could
do is we would use
a another program.
But this program would be
called an interpreter.
It would be running directly,
it's machine code and it's
running directly on that CPU.
And what that interpreter
program is doing is it's
looping over code in
our high level program.
And whenever it finds some code
in that high level program,
it will figure out
what actions it needs
to take to accomplish
its end goal,
right? That would
be an interpreter.
Now if you ask different people,
they'll probably give
you a simplified answer.
It might say something
like Python is
interpreted and
Java is compiled.
And that's not picture is
a little more complicated.
I'm going to show you
a complicated picture
now about how those do.
Both of them actually have
somewhat of a hybrid approach.
Okay, and that approach is that
we produce an intermediate
language called byte code.
So what we might do
here is we might
write some code up here,
feed it through a compiler.
And we get something byte code
which is closer to the
machine code, but not quite.
And then instead of having
an interpreter over here,
we're going to call this
a virtual machine now.
And what the virtual machine
will do is it'll help
translate this byte
code into machine code.
Lots of nice things about this.
One is that compile
this Spy code, I could
share it around,
and then if people
have computers
that understand different
machine code well,
as long as they have the
right virtual machine there,
they could run it, right?
One language that does
this is Python, right?
We don't often think about
Python being compiled,
but if you run Python three
in the name of a program,
it'll feed your Python code
through and it'll create
Python byte code.
Sometimes that'll even show up,
You might have noticed a
YC file at some point,
and then the Python
Virtual Machine
is going to start running
that code for you.
Let me just show you
what this looks like.
I'm going to head over here and
I'm going to jump into Python.
I am going to import disc,
which stands for disassembly.
And I can say disc, disc.
And I can put some Python code
here and I'm going to say
z equals x times two plus y.
What that will do is
it'll print off, well,
what is the byte code corresponding
to my Python program?
These last two lines
here. Ignore those.
It always does
that at the end of
any code that doesn't
really mean anything to us.
I'm going to look
at this up here.
What is this doing? It
has to load in the value
corresponding to x. I
have a name for that,
It has to load in a constant.
Value which is two, right?
So x times two.
It has to multiply
those together, okay?
So I've done this, it
has to load in Y, great.
And then it has to add
those together again,
and finally it stores
that all back in Z.
So just looking at this,
does anybody want to
ask what might I
reasonably think that
these X, Y, and Z are?
What type might they be?
There's one of the one.
Right answer. So I'm just
like looking for ideas.
Yeah, right here. Yeah, I
might think that there's
some kind of number.
Looks like we're kind of doing
some kind of math with it.
Right? Python? Are
there other things that
could be besides numbers?
Yeah, back here.
It could be strings
and oh, I didn't even
think about it being list,
but that's true too, right?
So this could be lots
of things, right?
So if this was a string,
then the string by
two would just repeat
the same string twice.
And then plus would
concatenate it.
And I guess you
go to a list two,
I'd repeat the list
multiple times.
So this byte, even though
it's closer to machine code
than my original Python,
there's lots of things that are
kind of missing there, right?
I don't know what types I'm
even dealing with, right?
So what I would
say is that Python
has fairly high level
byte code, right?
The Python Virtual
Machine is going
to have to figure out a
lot when it actually runs,
like what types are involved.
All right, so let's
take a look at Java.
And at first glance, Java
looks the same, right?
But there are a couple
of differences.
One is that this step of
running the Java compiler,
you actually have to think
about it as a programmer.
You have to run Java C or
another Java compiler
to produce the byroad,
That byroad does
class files and that
bytecode is trying
to have details
like what are the
types involved, right?
So it's probably faster
to run Java byroad on
the Java Virtual
Machine than it is to
run Python byroad on the
Python Virtual Machine.
Because this, this byte
code here is closer
to what the machine
actually wants.
All right, so we have
the picture like that.
Now I've shown a
couple paths now to
get from the user's code
on somebody actually
running on the machine.
And there's lots of
different paths to do that.
And then I can even add
them in this picture.
For example, Scala is
a language that some
of these systems
are built on like Spark.
And rather than building a brand
new Spark virtual machine,
they decided, well, won't we
just write this compiler that
converts it to JVM
byte code, right?
The Java Virtual Machine has
been around a long time.
People have really optimized it.
Why build something
new when you have
this great piece of
software, right?
So Scala fits there. This is
just kind of a wacky idea.
I don't think it's
gone anywhere,
but people have also built
something called the
jython from pilot.
I will take Python toad
and convert it to
byte toad, right?
So there's lots of
different paths here
that you could imagine,
but the end of the day is
that we have to somehow take
our program and run
it as machine toad.
Do you have any questions about
all these different ways
that things can run?
All right, great. All of
that's talking about code that
we're running on on CPU
central processing units.
But there are
alternatives to that.
One of the big alternatives,
the most popular one is GPUs.
They stands for Graphics
Processing units.
Both CPUs and GPUs have
cores in them, A CPU.
Those cores are
fairly powerful and
each core can be
doing its own thing.
On a GPU, we have lots and
lots of core, maybe thousands,
but they're not so fast and
they're very special purpose,
they just work well with floats.
I'm assuming that's what
they needed for graphics,
it turns out it also
helps a lot with
machine learning and
scientific computing.
In those kinds of cases,
I might be working on lots
of different data
at the same time,
but I'm doing the same thing
to all the different data.
So I've illustrated that by
tying these course
together, right?
Each core is working
on different data,
but it's doing the
same operations
at the same time, right?
So depending on what
you want, if you want
flexibility, you
might want to CPU.
In other cases, the GPU might
give you a lot more speed.
This book here, Python
Machine Learning
by Sebastian Rask,
actually used to be
a professor here,
did a comparison just between
one example CPU and one GPU.
Both of them have a clock
inside of them that's ticking.
And this is how
fast it's ticking.
Giga is billion this
hertz times per second,
so this 3.2 billion
times per second,
we can see that the clock in
the CPU is ticking faster.
That doesn't tell you as
much as you might think
because some cores might
take multiple clock ticks
to do one instruction,
and that's not
always comparable.
We can see again that
the CPU has eight cores,
this one has 3,000 cores.
If I really want to
compare these, well,
how can I actually say one
is faster than the other?
The only way to really
do it well is to take
an actual program and
run it on both and
see how fast it is.
Sometimes we write
programs that we
just run for the sake
of measuring speed,
and those programs are
called benchmarks,
An example of a benchmark
that will make a GPU.
Look really good, is
one that's doing a lot
of operations with floats.
And what it might measure is
how many floating
point operations
can you do per second, right?
You know, some are
faster, slower.
You have to find
some way to wait it.
There's some details
that I'm not trying to get into,
but I can tell how many floating
point operations can
I do per second?
And then we have all
these suffixes that,
or prefixes you might be
familiar with from
the metric system.
K is 1,000 is 1 million,
G is 1 billion and
is 1 trillion.
Just to make sure we're
understanding that
this one is 11,300 gigaflops.
What would that be in teraflops.
So we want to just shout it out.
11.3 terra flops, right?
So those are the
kinds of conversions
I want you to just
get comfortable doing
this semester that's
trying to show up with
Bytes and other units as well.
Won't we just do
a quick top hat to make sure
everybody's on the same
page with this one.
So I'm going to
bring this up over
here and don't worry
too much if there's technical
difficulties today,
This is just kind of a
trial run of using Top Hat.
And there we go.
Yeah. So we're just going
to give this a shot.
I just want you to convert
some units for me.
Yeah,
question right here.
Oh, why are they more efficient?
Oh, yeah, that's
a good question.
Um, yeah, I'll come back to
it after we finish the topic.
All right, cool. So
let me check this out.
And the answer is 700,
which is correct,
right? So 0.7 teraflops.
That is talking about
trillions of flops.
When I'm converting to
gigaflops, that's billions.
So when I go from
trillions to billions,
I have to multiply
it by 1,000 And that
gets me to the 700 again. Right.
I know there's more of you
here than answered this.
So just talk about
practice warm up today.
Yeah. And then there was a
question down here which was,
why does tying all of these
together make it faster?
And that's an
excellent question.
Why it does actually
make it faster?
I don't know if I know enough
about hardware to
say like why it is.
I can speculate a little bit
that when these cords are
executing instructions,
there's a bunch of steps to it.
Like you have to load in
the instruction itself and you
have to load in some data,
and then you have
to do a calculation
and maybe store something back.
And so what I'll speculate
is that at least
some of those steps that they
can be sharing that
same thing, right?
They're all doing the
same instructions.
So maybe it's faster to
load in the instructions,
but there's probably
a better answer
to that than I'm able to give.
Yeah, excellent question.
Other questions
people have about
either the top hat
or about GP's.
All right, cool.
Let's talk a bit
about memory here.
I have a bunch of six
of Ram down here.
Ram stands for Random
Access Memory.
What does random Random means?
You can jump around
and read data at
different places and that's
relatively efficient to use.
The opposite of that
would be a device that
I can only access sequentially.
Right? So I don't
know how many of you
have ever used a tape cassette.
But if I'm listening to a song
and I want to skip past a song,
it actually takes a long time to
fast forward past that song.
This is not a random
access device,
but Ram would be great at that.
I could very quickly switch
songs with no real delay.
Ram contains bits, and bets
are either zero or one.
If I have two bets, then I
guess I could get
different possibilities.
I could have 00011011.
In general, the formula
is that if I have bets,
there's two different possible
values I could have with it.
When I have a bunch of bets,
there's different ways
I can represent data.
Right here, what I'm
showing is for three bets,
there's eight different
combinations.
And I could say those
combinations might be indicating
a letter or maybe they're
indicating a positive number.
Or maybe they're
indicating a number
that is either
negative or positive.
This idea is representation. And
How we actually encode
and decode our data.
That's going to be
very important.
How do we encode and
decode our data?
Because we're going to
be dealing with a lot
of data this semester,
so we might see things
like when we're doing
floating point operations,
maybe we change our type
and we lose a little
bit of precision,
but all of a sudden we
take half as much Ram.
Or maybe we're sending data
over a network to another
computer and there are
some formats that will just
really squeeze
that down and send
the minimum possible
bets, right?
So this is going
to be coming back.
What are different ways we
can represent data and bets?
A lot of you, I'm guessing
all of you have
heard the word byte.
Byte is just referring
to eight bets.
So I could have 256
different possible values.
And what I say about Ram is
that it's byte addressable.
Every different byte
in Ram has a number or
an address associated with
it that I can use to look it up.
It's not bit addressable.
A bit doesn't have
its own address.
Bytes have an address,
What does that mean?
That means if I want to
access a single bit,
then first I have to use
the address for the byte,
grab that data and then do
some extra steps to
pull that bit out.
Accessing a single
bit is actually
slower than accessing
the whole bite.
We have the same prefixes
that we talked about
before for Gapp,
where we use those to measure
how many bytes we have,
1 kilobyte, it could
be 1,000 bytes,
or it could be 1024 bytes.
Why? Well, I think
that it's clear how
1,000 is a nice round
number for humans,
1024 is a power of two,
and that's a nice round
number for computers.
Good thing is that the
numbers are fairly close,
but people might mean one
or the other depending
on the context.
You might have to ask people
to clarify if they don't say,
but usually they're
pretty close in scale.
What are some
characteristics of Ram?
It's small so for example,
the most powerful virtual
machines will use this semester,
only have 4 gigabytes of Ram.
It's easy to imagine
our datasets being a
lot bigger than that.
When we're talking about big
data systems, it's volatile.
Volatile means that the data
gets lost whenever you reboot.
Whether you reboot
it intentionally
or from a crash, right?
So not a good place to
keep your long term data.
And it is fast,
that's, it's redeeming quality.
It's much faster than
storage devices.
And so as our programs
are actively running,
we're going to want to
keep our data in Ram.
All right, so we might
be keeping things like
Python lists or
data frames in Ram.
We're going to keep our
program code in Ram.
Another thing that we're
going to be talking
about later on
is that we might have
a huge data set,
say on a hard drive, and
it's too big to
fit it all in Ram,
but maybe certain parts of that
data are accessed more often.
What we could do then is we
could keep some of that hot.
Frequently axed data in Ram.
And that's going to
be called caching.
be a topic of another
lecture coming up soon.
All right, let's
talk about storage.
Here. On the left, I
have hard disk drives,
that's the older technology.
It has this spinning
magnetic platter here.
Depending on how
it's magnetized,
it could represent either zero
or one that's
constantly spinning.
And there's a head over
here that moves to
read bits at
different locations.
On the right hand side, I have
an SSD that stands
for Solid State disk.
It has no moving parts.
Everything is stored as
cells that are either
charged or not charged.
Because of that, it will
generally be a lot faster.
Both of these are what we
would call block devices.
Okay. When I was
talking about Ram,
I said that Ram is
byte addressable.
These are not byte addressable,
they're assiblet the unit of
blocks. How big is the block?
Well, different devices define
it differently, but, you know,
a half a kilobyte might be
a reasonable block size
or a few kilobytes.
So what that means is, as I'm
reading and writing
data to these,
I will grab a whole block at
a time or write back a
whole block at a time.
If I just want to
modify one byte,
that's just as expensive
as modifying the whole
thing, if not more.
So we have these block devices
where we store data.
These are huge.
Does anybody have any
device that's like
a terabyte or beggar
in your machine?
Anybody? A few people.
Right.
So it's kind of something
reasonable like you could draw
by a hard drive with a
terabyte of storage.
It's not insanely
expensive, it's non vital,
so a great place
for long term data,
if you reboot your data
will still be there.
Unfortunately, it's
very slow to access.
So this might be where
we're working with
large data sets or
any data that needs to
be preserved long term.
I've been talking about
the four main
resource categories,
but a lot of these have really
subcategories I
could think about.
So when I'm talking
about storage resources,
one thing I might be
talking about is just like,
how much space do
you have? Right?
And that would be measured
in units of bytes.
I could say, for
example, my hard drive
has 500 gigabytes
of storage space.
Another thing I might
talk about is throughput.
How quickly can I transfer
data to or from my device?
In that case, it's
going to be a rate,
it's going to be in terms
of bytes per second.
I might say, for example,
my hard drive can transfer
200 megabytes/second
The throughput
is going to depend a lot
on your pattern, right?
If you're just accessing
all your data
sequentially in order,
it might be pretty fast.
But if I'm accessing a byte
here and a byte there,
that throughput is going
to be much worse, right?
So we have to clarify,
just talking about the
best case throughput
or for a specific work load.
Another metric is latency.
And latency in this sense
is how long does it
take to actually
just fetch a small amount
of data, maybe from
my hard drive.
That might be something
like ten milliseconds.
Hard drives are much
cheaper than SSD's.
The gap is closing,
but there's still
about a six times
difference in twist.
And so I think that hard
drives are not going away,
at least in the near future.
Why? Because sometimes all I
care about is buying
a lot of capacity.
I don't care about other things.
Take for example,
Youtube, right?
There's some videos on Youtube
that are very popular.
It's seen all the time, but
there's also just
a lot of garbage
that maybe a couple of
people have watched
it a year ago and nobody
will ever watch it again,
but they can't delete it.
And so what do they
do if you're Youtube?
You buy an insane number of
hard drives and that's where
you keep all that cold data.
Right? So I think
both of these have
a story going forward at
a, for the near term.
All right. The last resource
I want to talk about
is network resources.
That's trying to be
really important when
we have this scale
out approach, right?
If I want to buy a bunch of
cheap machines and have them
work together in a cluster,
well, they have to talk to
each other over a network.
What does that
network look like?
Well, I could start
with an individual
server, an individual computer,
and if I need a bunch of them,
I could stack them
on top of each
other in a box like this.
That's called a rack.
And I have all these
servers stacked in here.
And you see at the
bottom, they all have
cables running down to
these boxes down here.
Those boxes are called switches
and because they're all
plugged into the same switch,
they can all communicate
with each other.
Right? All these
different servers
are communicating
with each other.
You know, if I have
very large data,
maybe one rack is not enough.
And so maybe I have
to have a data center
with many, many racks in there.
And then each of the racks
might communicate
with each other.
If I have two computers
in the same rack,
they can probably
communicate together more
efficiently than two
computers in different racks.
And so we have to
start to think about,
well, where do we
want to place things,
where do we want
our code to run,
where do we want our data to
live so that we
can be efficient?
Right? If I have a few
computers that are working
together and I put them
all in the same rack,
that's going to be faster.
Can anybody think
of a reason I might
not want to do that even
though it's faster?
Yeah, Right here.
Yeah. The systems
more vulnerable.
Right. If like, the power
supply for that rack goes down,
well, my data is
suddenly unavailable.
Right.
So we're going to be learning
systems like Cassandra this
semester that can think
very carefully, like, oh,
I have maybe data centers
in different continents that
are working with each other,
and then each of those
might have some racks.
And how do we spread out our
data to make it more safe,
right, In the case
of disaster, right?
And there's a fundamental
trade off there between
performance and the
safety of our data.
So this whole idea of like
how are all the computers
connected together
and which ones are
nearby each other farther away?
That's a question of topology.
One of the systems to
learn this semester
is the Hadoop file system.
And when you're configuring it,
you can tell it that, okay,
maybe I have this
router up here and
that's connecting a couple
of racks over here,
each of which has a
bunch of machines in it.
Right? Those are the
kinds of things you might
configure if you're working
at the scale of a data center.
What are some metrics that
we have for networking?
They're actually very similar
to what we have for storage.
Latency is generally the time
it takes to send a message
from point A to point B.
You could also talk about
the round trip time latency,
which would be maybe
sending a message
and then getting
the answer back.
We also have an
idea of throughput,
which another word for that in
the networking world that
we could use as bandwidth.
And that's a question
of how many bits
we could send per second.
So for example, I
might say I can
send 10 million bits
per second, right?
When I have this acronym MBPS.
Notice that's a little
bit different than
the throughput measure
we have over here.
This is capitalized on
the right hand side.
This is talking about bytes.
If I wanted to
rewrite this number
as MBPS, what would
the number be?
Yeah, right here it
would be 80, right?
Because there's
eight bits per byte.
So that's something
to be careful
if you're kind of like comparing
like how fast is my for
hard drives, right?
People talking about
megabytes per second.
For something like
this, networking people
usually talk about
megabits per second.
So be aware of that as you're
comparing and maybe
that'll all affect you
all in your personal lives as
you're paying for
Internet service as well.
Often if you have lower latency,
you probably have better
throughput as well,
but that's not always true.
Maybe I have two
computers that are
very near each other
with a weak link,
and maybe these two computers
are on opposite ends
of the Internet.
But I have a high bandwidth
to send data across it, right?
So it might take a long time
for the data to get across,
but when it does, it'll
be a flood of data.
All right, those
are the overview of
the resources and we're
spending a third of
the semester to
look at all these
resources in more detail.
The other piece I want to talk
about today is deployment.
How do we actually run
our code somewhere?
What we're going
to be doing this
semester is we're going to be
renting virtual machines
on Google's cloud, right?
And by renting, well, you
will get $100 of free credit.
So you aren't going to
have to pay for it.
But what Google
does is they'll buy
these physical machines and
then rent virtual
machines on them,
and you're going to be running
a Linux virtual machine on that.
I think everybody
has hopefully used
a virtual machine
either from 320 or 400,
otherwise I'm sure folks
will figure it out.
So we're going to have those
and we can't really afford
100 credits is not enough for us
all to have like a cluster
of virtual machines.
So we're going to
use another piece
of software called Container.
We're multiple lectures
actually on containers.
For now, you can
think of containers
as a lightweight
virtual machine.
And the easiest way to run
containers is with a tool
called Docker, right?
So going to have these
Docker containers and
what we'll do is you'll have
your virtual machine and
you'll have all these
little containers on it
representing almost
like different machines
in your cluster.
So what it'll feel
like is you have
a small cluster of
computers and you can get
comfortable working
in this kind of
environment and practice
with that accordingly.
Right, So a few
responsibilities you're
going to have this semester.
I may be relatively hands
off with this because I
think everybody has seen virtual
machines in other
classes before.
You're going to have to
create your virtual machine
and when we switch size,
you'll have to recreate it.
You can choose what
region you want to go in.
I go with Iowa
because it's nearby
and it's a low CO
two emissions site.
You're going to figure out
how to connect it with SSH.
And you can help with
all of this too,
like during office
hours and stuff too.
But this is just general stuff
that I expect people to know how
to know or learn right,
how to work with.
You're going to have
to install software
and do reboots after updates.
You're going to have to back
up your work somewhere.
Like you could back it up
on a private repository on
Thub or the tool
SCP that I'm going to
talk about next time.
And then sometimes
Drew will have
various issues with you
for whatever reason.
They always think everybody's
trying to crypto
mine, who knows?
Maybe they are, but
they'll like shut you
down and then you have to
appeal sometimes and say,
I wasn't doing it And
then they're like,
okay, we believe you.
Anyway, I can't really
get involved in that.
I've tried to, and
they don't like me to.
So that happens, you'll work
with Google to sort that out.
But, you know, I think most of
the time it goes
pretty smoothly.
And we're always
here to help during
office hours if there's issues.
So awesome, I'll be
sending messages soon
about how to get started
with your virtual machine,
and otherwise, have
a great evening.