We introduced this
idea of caching,
which comes about because
we have different ways,
places we can store by.
Some are faster,
some are slower,
and the faster ones
tend to be smaller.
So what we'll often do
is have the majority of
our data in one storage medium,
and then we'll have
a subset of that
in some faster technology.
And that, of course,
raised a policy question.
We have to have a policy
of what data gets to
be logged in the
faster medium, right?
And so we learned a couple of
different policies last time.
We learned Fifo and LRU.
And today I want to spend a
little more time on those.
Last time, you know, we ran out
of time after the top
hat to go through it.
So I'd go to go through that
a couple more examples.
Try to understand
when these policies
might work well or
when they might not.
And then we're going to move to
how could we actually write
code to make this policy
a reality, right?
So how could we write
code that does LRU,
that's be setting you up.
Well, for your project three
that's be released this
Friday because there
you're writing some
policy code for a cache.
Then what I want to do is
I want to look at a new,
well I guess it's
new to this course.
I added a lecture this
semester on Pero.
Pero is this Python package
that is cash aware.
It tries to use a CPU cache
in a very efficient way.
It lets you use such
that the operating system is
using in a very efficient way.
So I want to give that type
of hands on like, okay,
here's something practical you
could walk away with that,
you could start taking
advantage of some of these
things that we're learning.
All right, so I might head
over here to my document
Abra last time you
all did this problem.
So I just want to work
through it and see
if anybody has any
questions about it.
There's a few things I see here.
I see that we're doing a Fifo
cache and it's size three.
And then this is our workload.
And so the first thing
we have to do is
we have to figure out
which ones are hits.
And then from that we can
contribute a hit rate.
And then based on
what the hit rate is,
we could say, well, what
is the average latency?
Because the hit has some
latency that's pretty fast.
And then there's going
to be a bigger latency
for the Mrs. first off,
there's no W in the cache.
That's a mess. I add
it to the cache.
Another. Okay, that's
straight, It's there.
That's a X not in the cache.
Add it first As,
then add it, then Y
not in the cache.
I'm going to mess and then add
it again. Y is right there.
That's A, then Z.
Z is not in the cache,
so it's a mess.
I'm going to add it here.
Now that's a problem because I
have too many
entries in my cache.
Can somebody just remind me?
Maybe everybody can just
shout out, who should I ev.
Excellent. Right,
so I'm, because
the most recent data is on
this side and the older
data is on this side.
So now I'm going to have y.
And Y is a hit, so that's good.
And then everybody
can either nod
their head yes, or
shake their head, no.
Do I have to move Y?
No, because this is
first in, first out.
First in, first out doesn't
share when I use things,
it just cares about
when it.in Right.
If I was doing LRU,
I would move it over here.
But this isn't
LRU, this is Fifo.
I have an X and that's
a head as well.
Right? And I don't have to move
my X either. So let
me tout this off.
I have 12344/8 equals 0.5 Great.
I was able to figure out what
percentage of them are hits,
and then based on some
additional information,
I can see what the
average latency was.
Half of the time it took
me 20 milliseconds,
and then half of the time it
took me 0.1 milliseconds.
Right, And what does
that equal? That will be
10.05 milliseconds on average.
Right? Lots of questions
I could ask you.
I could ask which ones
are specifically hits.
I could ask what
the hit rate is.
I could ask how does that play
out in terms of actual performance
at the end of the day?
So what questions do people
have about this problem?
All right, so let's look at
some other use cases here.
I'm right to drove
through this one
a little bit faster now because
we've spent some time
on the basic idea
of how you step through
it and trace it.
So what I want to do now is just
try to walk through it
quickly and then see,
make some observations about we
LRU is doing well
or what it's not.
I'm got look at this,
I see I have a
cash of size four.
What is the pattern? It's
34567, then repeat 34567.
So I can see that the
first five are all Mrs.
because the first
time you access
anything has to be a mess.
Right. And then
whatever was least
recently used gets
bumped out and
whatever is most
recently used stays in.
I guess what we'll be staying
in is 45674567, right?
So the first half
of that's where I
got to no hits so far.
So now I have a three,
which is a real shame because
I just bumped three out,
but I guess three is a
mess. Bring it back in.
Four? Uh. Oh, Well,
I guess that's a miss too.
Another shame because I
had just kicked four out.
So I'm going to put four
here and bump this one out.
This keeps happening to me.
So there's a five, all right?
I have a six. I had
just taken six out,
but now it's back seven.
Same deal, right?
You get the idea. It's a
repeating pattern, right?
And my hit rate is a big
whopping zero. All right?
Lru, when you first learn
about the policies,
LRU feels like the
smartest one, right?
It's like, well, it
takes into account
that I've been using
this a lot recently.
But this is the one big pattern
that LRU is really bad at,
when a program keeps
scanning the dataset
multiple times and the dataset
is too big for the cache.
Can we saw a use
case this semester?
We keep scanning the same
dataset over and over again.
Can anybody refresh my memory?
When might we have to do that?
Yeah, right here.
Matrix multiplication.
Yeah, I think that
might be a case.
I haven't thought
through enough, right?
But yeah, we might have
to because I guess we use
the same columns on
many different rows.
Right. So we might
keep scanning it.
So yeah, I think that's
true, right? Absolutely.
Right. We didn't drove
through that. Are there
other other examples that
people can think of?
Yeah, right back
here. What's that?
Maybe, I mean, maybe you have
to keep scanning a web page.
Yeah. Who knows?
Maybe you do it
and then you wait awhile
and scan it again. Yeah.
Is there a hand up front
here? What's that?
Yeah. Training epoch.
That was the one that
trying that came to mind.
I think all these
are right answers.
But in machine learning, right,
You can't just make one pass
over the data and
learn everything.
You keep looking
at the same data
again and again and
again and again.
If you shuffle your batches,
maybe it's not so bad, right?
But if you aren't shuffling
and you have that
training epoch,
you're gonna get into
exactly this problem for
a very standard machine
learning access pattern, right?
So this is a real pattern.
It happens, it's common.
Lru is really bad at it.
We had learned, well,
I guess what about Fifo?
Would Fifo be any
better at this?
People can shake their
head. Yes or no?
Fifo, help me here.
No, thank you.
Fifo is just as bad, right?
Because Fifo will
have that same thing.
We keep kicking it out.
The third pattern that
we had talked about
very briefly was that we
could randomly ev something,
when evi just choose one,
randomly bump it out.
That would actually be quite
a lot better here, right?
Because, you know,
80% of our data,
four fifths of our data
fits in the cache.
And if we're doing it randomly,
then kind of long term would
take some time to warm up.
But on average, I'd
probably be getting
about in a 80% hit
rate long term.
So random just feels
like a stupid policy,
but in some cases it would be
a smart policy like LRU, right?
So it all depends on
what your workload is.
All right, let's take
a look at this one.
This is actually exactly
the same problem,
but now I have a
cache size five.
All right, so I have 34567,
then repeat without even
tracing through this.
Can anybody tell me what the
hit rate is going to be?
Yeah, right here half.
All right, so our entire
dataset fits in memory,
which is good. It
fits in the cache.
But we still, even if we have,
you know, the best
possible case,
we have a huge, even
the biggest caches
have to have some time
to warm up. All right?
So it'll see those half
those items first,
it won't be there, and
then the second pass
through it will all be in there.
And the longer I run, the more
I can benefit from that cache.
All right, cool. Do people have
any last questions about
these cash policies?
All right, well I
want to work through
a programming example
because I know
you're going to have to do
this on your project soon.
And I think it will
help you to see some
code read in to get a
sense of how this is done.
And of course, I'll
post the notebooks on
line afterwards.
So I have some starter
code for this one.
This was originally going to
be lecture nine,
which was last time.
So I'm going to copy
from down here.
I'm sure to copy this
whole big example.
I'm going to paste it down here.
And there's a couple of
different things going on,
so I'm just going
to split it up.
So I'm going to have that
piece and then this piece down
here. What are we doing?
We're doing request. So some of
you might have seen
that if you have
more Python background,
but that's just
downloading this web page.
And I'm going to open this
up and see what's there.
And it turns out what it
contains is a bunch of
different ID's for
weather stations.
So what we want to do
is for one of these
weather stations,
we want to look up the weather
weather that it's having.
Okay? And so that's what
this is doing down here.
We have this other URL which
takes us to the weather data.
And then we can put in different
names here because it's
a format string to get that.
All right, so what is
it doing down here?
So first I'm checking,
was there a status code?
Sometimes when you're fetching
things from a website,
the server responds
and says four oh four,
I don't have it for me.
I would rather crash
than try to parse out
that error page because it
doesn't have the data I want.
So if we get past this line,
which sometimes
raises an exception,
I was able to successfully
grab the page
and it has text
which I can analyze.
And so I'm splitting that up by
the new line character to
get a bunch of stations.
And then we're randomly
picking ten different
stations. Random sample.
And then from those
stations we're
sampling from those 10100 times.
Right? So those ten might, well,
they'll definitely
have a bunch of
repeats on them to
get to 100, right?
So if I look at it down here,
I have my stations here,
just ten and then my work
load right there will be some
repeats down here, I guess.
Like this one repeats with two.
This one repeats with
this one, right?
Repeats. That's fairly common
because I put some
weights here, right?
Of these ten stations,
one of them is going to
appear 30% of the time,
the other one will
be 20% of the time.
And then the rest all
have equal weight.
So I'm just trying to
slice this so it's
handy so we can see
it there. All right.
Now, if you were
writing a real program,
it would probably
have a genuine reason
to go be downloading
these pages.
And I don't want to get into
the complexity of that.
So I'm just trying to assume
that there's some program and it
needs to access these weather
stations in this order.
And what I want to
do is see how we can
do it efficiently, right?
You see it's repeatedly
downloading a lot
of the same things.
Can we cache them so we
don't have to do
it more than once?
All right, so let
me just come down here
and see how this works.
I'm going to grab the
first weather station.
I can just paste
that right here.
When I do that, I
should be able to get
a data frame and maybe just
look at the first
three rows of it.
Pandas has a read CSV that can
fetch these things
for us, right?
So I was able to
grab some weather
there and I was just like, oh,
okay, I have some
kind of warning,
I won't worry too much about it.
Great. So I was able to do that.
Maybe there's something
weird about that file.
I'm just trying to grab
a different set set
of them so we aren't
dealing with that.
Is that all of them? They
all have that. That's weird.
I don't think that was
popping up this morning.
Anyway. Not a problem, right?
That we can have an error,
they're not a big deal.
What I want to do
is that instead of
having whoever is doing
this work directly
called read CSV,
I want a function that can take
a station name and then
give them that data frame.
And they won't even have
to think about caching,
but my function will
do that for them
if they call it with
the same station name.
It might be faster
the next time, right?
So let's do that.
I'm going to write a
function called it station.
And that's going to
take a station name.
And then what I'll do
is I'll just copy this.
To get my data frame,
I will return it down here.
I'm going to get that data
frame and I'm going to return
it. Let's just try this.
I'm going to say it station,
and then I'm going to
try this one right here.
All right? I'm going
to do that again.
I'm just trying to figure out
why it started doing this.
Maybe if I say this little
memory thing, it'll be fine.
Will it be quiet
then? Okay, great.
So I'm going to do that and
then it won't complain.
And we don't tend too many
details about that right now.
It might be something
we come back to later.
Right? But I can see, okay,
you grab that station, great.
Now what I can do is I can add
some caching capabilities
to this function,
and the user won't have
to worry about it.
Right?
They'll call the function the
same way they always have.
The way I often like to do
a cache is to create
a dictionary.
May be called cash, right?
Say cash going to
be a dictionary.
And one of the most useful
comments I think when
you're creating a
dictionary is say
what the keys and
values are going.
Say the keys are
station name and
the value is drawing to B
data frame for that station.
All right, so what
I should do is
that after I grab
the data frame, I
should put it in there.
I should say the cache of
the station should equal
that data frame. I
might add it there.
If I run this, then if
I look at my cache,
I can see grade, It has this key
here and an associated
data frame with it.
So I remembered it somewhere
if somebody wants to
go get it again. All right.
So that's good.
Right now though,
I'm not actually using
my cash anything,
putting something in there,
but not pulling anything out.
And so I should have
a big F statement up
here that can handle two cases.
Right, So if this station
is in the cache, then what?
Then I guess I have a
hit, which is cool.
Otherwise what if it's
not in the cache?
Then it's a mess.
So those are the two
scenarios, right,
And all this code
I wrote so far,
it's actually doing
the slow work
of going out to the
Internet and grabbing that.
So this is the kind
of code that I would
put on this miss path.
All right, so I'm going
to put this down here,
so I missed in my cache,
I'm going to grab that data
frame and then return it.
All right, maybe
I'm trying to put
some print statements
up here so I can
see what's happening a
little bit more easily.
And then up here I'm
trying print head.
All right, so now I figure
out what I want to
do in this case.
All right, so one of
the things I could do
is I could just return cache
of station because I
know that that's the data
frame that I'm looking for.
One thing that I think will make
our code easier in general,
and I think is a
good practice when
it's not too difficult is
to just have one exit point
from your function, right?
So if I only have one
exit point down here,
then the code just just
a little easier to read.
And if I later come
along and I want to
measure how long the
function takes to run,
it's easier for me to
do those measurements.
All right, so I have this.
And let's just give it a shot,
right? So I have this one.
Let's try it again a few times.
The first time it was a
miss. That was kind of slow.
And then it was pretty
fast. It got these hits.
All right, So I have a cache,
I can add things to it, I
can make my code faster.
And if you have lots of memory,
something like this, a
little function like this
might save you a
lot of time, right?
And you might not even have
to worry about evicting
because you have lots
of resources, right?
So people write toward
like this all the time.
All right. Any question?
I guess there's like maybe
some Python stuff
is new to people.
I know some people are coming
from a Java background.
And any questions
about this code
before I think about eviction?
All right, cool. When
do I have to ev?
Sometimes I have
to ev Down here,
if the length of the cash
is bigger than something,
then I have to ev, right?
Because I don't
have enough space.
Okay. Well, how big is my cash?
I think for now I'm just
going to say that I have
some cash size that's
fixed up here.
I'll say that's like
five to say cash.
In a realistic scenario,
you'd be kind of
thinking about how
big these data frames
are and how much memory you
have and evicting accordingly.
Right? But we'll just
say it's a fixed size.
For now, I have that
and then I have to,
how do I ev, maybe I'll make
this comment up here. All right.
So I'll say, should we
ev if I want to evict,
I have to find a
victim Right, somehow.
And then what do I have to do?
I have to remove
it from the cash,
let me say cash dot pop victim.
Right. This is a key
in that dictionary,
is trying to remove the value
associated with that key.
All right, so how do
I do this up here?
Well, what I need to do is
I need to have some sense
of when this item was actually
added to my dictionary, right?
Python dictionaries actually
keep track of that.
Now they can show you
the insertion order.
But for simplicity
I'm just trying to
assume that I need a separate
data structure for that.
So what I'll do up
here is I'll say that
I have an evict order up here.
And I'll make a comment
here that start
of list contains
items to be evicted.
End of list is freshest.
All right? I have that.
What do I want to do?
Well, I want to take the
very first item off of here,
so I'm going to say
evict order pop.
And in this case I
have index zero.
All right, so this is
pop from the front.
I just trying to make
a little note here.
I'm going to say to do,
use a faster data
structure for evict order.
That is not order in
for pop zero, right?
Whenever I have a Python list
and I pop something
from the beginning,
every other item has to
shift to the left, right?
Because we need to have a
new value at item zero.
I'm not trying to worry
about that much for now.
Right. And honestly, when I
have a short list like this,
shifting everything over is
incredibly fast compared
to downloading something
from a web page.
Right. So I think that's fine.
Right. All right.
So I think we're in
pretty good shape, right?
We have our hit case,
we have our mis case.
And what policy can
anybody help me out
with what policy
I've implemented so far?
This is yeah, right here,
it's close to an LRU.
I'm definitely kind of
kicking out the data that's
been there in there for a while.
But Yeah, go ahead.
First in, first out.
It's first in, first out
and they're very similar.
Right? So the difference is, is
that right here if
you're trying to
distinguish LRU and fo you
look at when somebody
hits in the cache,
do they have to move it around?
And right now I don't
do it. Right? So this
is a fo policy.
All right, so what
I want to do now,
I want to loop over all
the stations, right?
So I'm say for station
in my workload,
I'm going to print off what
that station is and I have
a bunch of them. That's cool.
What I want to do is I want
to get a data frame for it.
Right? I say data frame,
it will be for that station.
I'm going to do that.
I should get a bunch
of hits or Mrs. maybe
what I want to show is that
after each of these what
I'll print is what
station it was.
And then I want to show what's
inside of my evict order.
Right? That will kind
of give me insight
into the state of the cache.
All right, so I have a problem,
which is what I think I
meant to add this up here,
but that shouldn't be
breaking things that badly.
Right. Okay. So I think
I missed one thing,
which is that when we
add it into the cache,
I also need to update
my evict order.
Right, So my evict order
should append that station.
Right, so I added
and then I also
have a sense a pend
goes to the end,
so that means this is
the freshest station.
Right, so I do.
Now I can see that things
keep getting added to
the cache until
it's of size five.
Right, in this case,
right, I was hitting
in the cache, right?
So this one hit in the
cache is right there.
And then what about, when
do I actually have
to change the cache?
Oh, here we actually
get to size five.
Okay, so I think that let
me find a miss down here.
Okay, so this one
is where it gets
a little interesting, right?
I was accessing this one,
it was not in the cache.
So what do we have to do?
We had to bump this
one out, right?
We did, we missed, and that
one got evicted, right?
So it was different.
And then what happened?
Four. These four all
shifted Laugh to be the
four to make room for this
one at the end, right?
You can walk through
and you can see,
is it doing the
correct thing, right?
Let me come up here and I'm
going to simplify it a bit.
One of the things
I want to do, I
want to see all
this on one line.
I say, I'll say n
equals that way it
won't print a new line.
After each of these, I can see
a little bit more C on
one line As it's running,
we're getting a bunch of
hits and Mrs. All right.
What questions do people
have about our cash so far?
I think it's a complete
working bio cash.
All right. Cool.
When we have cashes,
we want to have some way to
evaluate how well they're doing.
Some statistics I'm
really interested
in is like how often
do I hit in the cash?
And also what is
my average latency
'my add some variables
for that first stats.
One of the stats will
be, do I have hits?
This will be true as a
hit and false is a miss.
And then I'm going to
have some latencies
here like that, right?
This is in milliseconds.
What I want to do in each
scenario is I have to
update these when I'm up
here. Then I had a hit.
I may say hit pen, true.
Maybe I'll just do that right
right underneath my print,
so it's in the same
place in each of them.
Then down here, I
know it's a mess.
My pen false.
So I'm going to get
some stats like that.
Then for the latencies, I
want to do some timing.
If I want to do some timing,
I have to import, whoa,
what happened there?
I have to import time.
If I want to time
this whole thing,
I can do a start time
up here, down here.
I can end time,
I can say n equals time time.
Then we'll tell me how
many seconds since
1970 or something like that
I mentioned earlier, right?
I'd like to have just like one
it point for my functions,
the data frame that makes it
really easy to
come along and add
this timing information
after the fact.
All right, so I think
that the number of
milliseconds is minus start.
That'll be in seconds.
I should multiply that by
1,000 and then I can
append it to my stats.
Right, I think you
are all going to be doing
this on the project,
but you do have a multi
threaded thing going on,
so you have to do some locking
when you're collecting
these stats.
All right, so I'm going to
do that and run this again,
and then I should be able to
get a bunch of stats out of it.
All right, cool.
So I've collected
a bunch of information so
I can look at my hits.
If I sum these up,
it will treat a true like
a one false like a zero.
So that will tell me I had 57
hits, however many, right?
So I have a 57% hit ratio.
What about the average
latency actually?
Right? The sum of the
latencies divided by
the length of the latencies
is the average latency.
Oh, quite a bit
faster in the morning,
actually. That's interesting.
All right, so I can
get these stats and
then tell you how
the cash is doing.
That would also let me do
things like say like if I made
the cash size three
instead of size two,
all right, let's
try it again and
see What I think will happen is
that hit rate
should down, right.
Smaller cash, fewer hits.
And as a result, like
my latency should draw
up, is that true?
Okay, my hit rate went down.
My latency went up not horribly.
And that's because
with this cache,
I was working with
data where there are
two popular items, Right?
So if I went like
below that size of how
many are popular,
I'd have a problem.
But there's probably diminishing
returns after I add more
and more. All right.
So this was a five foot cash.
And do people have any questions
about how to write
toad like that?
Oh, all right.
So what I want to do now is
I want to copy all of this
and make a very small
change that's trying to
turn it into an LRU, right?
So LRU and this is
exactly the same.
Except for the case, right?
I have to make some changes in
here and I have to make a
change to the evict order.
Right? With Fifo, we don't
really care if
somebody is using it.
We just care about when
it got added with LRU.
We're actually seeing
when it's used,
when did somebody
actually look it up?
What we'll have to do down
here is we'll have to
say I have to remove an item.
What I'm going to do is I'm
going to remove that station.
Right?
So I might be somewhere in
the middle of that list.
Then I'm going to
pend it to the end.
Right? So however fresh it was,
maybe kind of like, you know,
average freshness
somewhere in the middle.
Pulling it out of the middle,
adding it to the end.
This is the most fresh
data that should
be like the last
thing to be evicted.
And so now we can do an
interesting experiment,
and we can run all
of this again.
And then we can compare it.
We can see which of
these caches is better,
what policy is better
for us, right?
So that's 47% hit ratio.
So LRU seems like
it's doing a little
bit better than Fifo.
It's kind of a smarter
policy, right?
It knows that there
are somebody that are
popular that get
access more often.
And we also have
lower latency, right?
So it's not always true.
Lru is often better than Fifo.
But in this case, I can
actually back that up.
You might do an experiment
and see otherwise.
But then you can say,
like for this work flow,
this is the kind of cash
policy I want to have.
Alright? So I'm
trying to her up here
again to show these
small changes
I made and I think you're
going to be doing LRU and
the sweet change at the
last minute on the project,
or you're going to have to
implement an L LRU cache,
a multi threaded LRU cache
to make it more interesting.
Yeah, so what
questions do people
have before you go off
and do it on your own?
All right, cool.
So I'm going to head over here,
I want to do some slides
and I'm going to start
talking about Pero.
Pero is going to help us
make more effective uses
of both the CPU cache
and the caching that's happening
inside of the operating system.
All right, so a little bit
of background here, right?
We want to start
writing more cash
friendly co and most of
us will be about Piero.
I'm going to show an
example of Pytorch.
Again, to get good use of the
operating system caching,
we have to learn about something
called memory mapping.
Pero definitely isn't
the only system
that can do memory mappings,
but it makes for a nice example.
Then for some data,
if we want it to
be cached or not,
we have to enable
something called swapping.
All right, so I'm going to
show how we can do swapping.
And then finally, I want to
show how we can set up doctors
that a container has
limited memory consumption.
All right, so first I'm
going to start with the CPU.
And remember that the CPU
typically we'll have
three levels of caching,
L1l2 and L three.
And I want to see how
data is actually being
accessed in there.
And so one of the
policy questions
was when we should evict things,
right, or when we should
load things into the cache.
Another question is if I just
access one byte of data,
say it's like a
letter in a string,
would I just bring that letter
by itself into the cache?
Or would I bring maybe
like the whole string or
some other amount of data?
And there's a bit of a
trade off here, right?
If I just access a
small bit of data and
that small bit of data
is the only thing
I read into the cache.
Then pretty soon I'm
probably going to
read the next letter.
And then I'd have another
cache miss and another one.
Right? So if you go
too fine grained,
your cache will probably
have a lot of Mrs.
Right. On the other hand,
if I access this
tiny little bite
and I pull in like
a whole megabyte,
well, I'm probably not
like that surrounds it.
I'm probably not going to
use most of that data.
So that's wasteful too, right?
So there's some kind of
granularity or sweet spot that we
try to go for and
the name for that,
for that amount of
data that we pull in.
It's generally fixed. It's
called a cache line, right?
So modern CPU's typically have
a cache line of 64 bytes, right?
So if I read one byte string up,
pull in 64 bytes,
a 64 byte chunk of
memory that reads it
into the cache, right?
You know, older CPUs
sometimes would have bigger
or smaller cache lines.
Again, it's not like bigger
or smaller is better, right?
It kind of depends on
what you're doing.
There's some kind of sweet spot.
For a long time,
most modern CPUs are
64 apples experimenting now.
Like in their latest max,
they're trying 128 again,
so kind of bringing that
back, that size, right?
But you could kind of the
order of magnitude, right?
We're not talking
like kilobytes,
we're talking about 100 or
so bytes at the most, right?
How big is that? Well,
64 has eight bytes,
and so I could have 864 integers
inside of a cache line.
Let's think about
what this would do in
terms of cache hits
and cache Mrs.
I have three examples
here, right?
In each case, I'm going to
start on the left hand side.
Maybe it's a little bit
of a confusing picture,
but what I'm imagining
is that 1664,
all in memory
following each other.
They're all contiguous, right?
They're all in a row in
memory. I have a program.
That is accessing four numbers.
Maybe my program just
says like A plus
B plus C plus D.
Very simple program.
And so the numbers
that it's accessing,
I put that in bold, red.
And then the numbers
that it's not
accessing right now are black.
Right? See it's accessing
these four numbers.
And then what I've
done is I've drawn
these red boxes around
all the numbers to
indicate a cache line.
Right? So numbers that are on
the same box are part
of the same cash line.
So that's set up.
My question for you
all is this program
that adds A plus
B plus C plus D,
how many hold up some
number of fingers,
how many cache lines are
we going to have to
load in to do this?
I'm seeing very few hands up.
The people who are putting
their hands up are
saying one, which is correct.
Right. All the
numbers I wanted to
access are part of
the same cash line.
Right. So when I access
the first number,
there will be a cash mess.
I'll load in the
whole thing. And then
when I access the
other three numbers,
they're already in the cash.
Right. So I wouldn't
have any more mess.
It's just one cash mess and
I would roll it in
this cash line.
So I'm going to
take some questions
because I think
a lot of people seem confused,
so Any clarifications about how
the cash lines work or about
this specific example?
Yeah, right back here. Load.
Yeah, exactly. Right. So
whatever the eviction policy is,
that whole cash line will get
evicted at the same time, right?
So this is kind of like the
granularity of data that
we used to bring into the cache
and evict out of the cash.
Absolutely. Yep, Yeah,
what other questions
do people have?
All right, let's
try another one.
So in this case I'm just
adding two integers.
Maybe it's like X plus Y.
And I'm wondering, right, if
we start with
nothing in the cash,
how many cash Sss will I be,
will I have in order
to add X plus Y?
Hold up some number of fingers.
I'm seeing a few people
say two, which is correct.
Right. Even though I'm
accessing two numbers,
only two numbers, they are
each and there are
different cash lines.
That means I have to load in
two complete cash lines to
be able to do this, right?
So adding these two numbers
is probably actually a lot
slower than adding four of them
in the previous example.
That makes sense.
What questions do
people have about that?
I'm seeing lots of
confused faces,
but if anybody has
any questions,
that would help the
whole room, I think.
All right. Let's look
at this last case.
In this case, we're accessing
every single number.
How many cash Mrs.
will there be assuming
nothing starts in the
cash? I'm seeing some two.
Which is correct, right?
This one will have two.
Second example and third example
are probably actually
pretty close in
performance because cash
miss is going to be
slower usually than just doing
some simple arithmetic
on the CPU.
All right, so let's
see how this plays
out in real programs.
And I found this great blog
that had this school plot.
I'm just trying to borrow that.
I don't think I could have
come up with anything
better myself.
Is it just like a
one line example?
But it shows a huge
difference in performance.
So what is this program?
I think this isn't like C sharp
or some other language,
but we can still read it.
We see we have a loop
that goes from position
zero up until the
length of some array.
And I guess like you could
have plus equal one,
but here it's plus
equal k. And in
the blog posts they
change what is right?
So I might index is like 01234.
Or if k is two,
then I would go 0246.
Right? So I'm doing that quick
background, these are 32.
32. How many bytes are in 3024?
I'm seeing some four, which
is correct. So how many?
32. Can I fit in a cash line?
Somebody can just shout it out.
I heard a couple of people
say 16, which is correct.
Right? It's like
cash lines 64 bytes,
four bytes for each
of these integers.
So each cache line
has 16 of these.
Okay, so let's think
about what happens.
We're looping over
this big array
and whenever we
land on a number,
we multiply it by three.
The bigger the K, the
less work we do, right?
If I make k twice as big,
I only have to look at half as
many integers until I get
to the end of the ray,
right? So what happens?
So what we do is we measure
on the x axis what k is.
Then on the y axis, we see
how long it takes to do so.
What's really interesting
is you go from one.
Up until 16. You're
doing a lot less
multiplying but
it doesn't matter
because what dominates
performance is your cash Mrs.
Right multiplying, that's
fast cash Mrs. slow
and cash line is 16 integer.
So anywhere 1-16 you
have the same number of
cash Mrs. only after that.
Let's say I go up to 32,
then that means I can
access this cash line,
skip one, access a
cash line skip one,
and then all of a sudden
I can be a lot faster.
All right, so what do
you want to start doing?
Start thinking in terms of not
the variables you're accessing.
How many cash lines is
your program accessing?
Don't just think about the
math you're doing on it,
because what really is often
slow is those memory accesses.
All right? Yeah, I thought
it was a very cool plot.
Any, any questions about
the plot experiment?
All right. Yeah, right here.
Oh yeah, that's a good question.
So there's ways that you
can just directly look up.
You can say on this
computer like like what
is the cash line size,
right? So you can do that.
And then here, right,
I guess if I didn't
know that information,
I think you could also infer
that the cash line
is 64 bytes, right?
So, so you could do
this little experiment
and you could try to see
what is really going on,
right? Yeah, great question.
You could do like a little
detective work, right?
All right, so that
was one example.
Just trying to illustrate
it. Let's look
at something that's
more realistic.
That we might
actually want to do
lots of things that
you might be working
with matrices, right?
Like num pi or pitorch
or whatever, right?
It's all kind of similar.
And when I create a matrix,
I think of it as two
dimensional, right?
Maybe I think of
it as a bunch of
rows stacked on top
of each other, right?
So in my mind it's
two dimensional.
But when I put data
in actual Ram,
Ram is just one
dimensional, right?
I put one bite after another.
So this is what I
kind of imagine.
But when I look at a virtual
addrespace'sj, you know,
one row laid one
after another, right?
They just kind of more
all consecutive, right?
So that's how things
would actually get
laid out in my virtual
address space.
Now I want to think
about what would
happen as I'm doing
different operations.
Sometimes I might
want to look in
a single row and add up
all the numbers in a row.
If I'm doing that,
that's a fast operation
because each of these rows
is using consecutive bytes.
And every time I have to
read in a cache line,
it's going to contain
a bunch of numbers in
the same row which I
need for my calculation.
Right? So I can very quickly
add up all the numbers in a row.
That's a cash
friendly thing to do.
Now what's not as
great is if I want to add up
all the numbers in a column,
because what will that mean?
That means that I
have to look at
one value in this row
and one value over
here in this row,
one value in this
row, like each time I
jump so far that I'm in a
different cash line, right?
Each time I'm
loading in 64 bytes,
then I only use like
four bytes of that as
part of my calculation.
Adding all the numbers
in a row, fast,
all the numbers in a column,
that's slow, even if
it's a square matrix.
Okay, Does that make sense?
Why one way is faster
than the other?
Do people have any
questions about that?
All right, so what
can you do about it?
Well, there's different
ways you can create
your tensors or
rays, or matrices.
One way you could do it, I
have two different ways.
I'm create exactly
the same thing.
On the left hand side, I
have this one where 123456,
if I just do it like
that, it's trying to
lay row after row after row.
Now, we talked earlier
on how you know,
Pytorch, a lot of these things
have a transpose feature.
When you transpose a matrix,
they don't want to have to
create a copy of the data.
That's a little bit
wasteful, right?
So what happens when
I transpose a matrix?
They just create like
a small little object
that just says, oh, what am I?
I'm that matrix over
there transposed.
And so if you look up in
me coordinates at x Y,
I'll just look at that one and
I'll tell you the value at yx.
Transposing does not
change memory layout,
it just adds a small
little piece of
information that it remembers
that it was transposed.
Okay, so we can take advantage
that's useful of itself,
but we can take advantage of it.
There's a trick we can do.
So what we could do is we
could take our column value.
In the column I have 135 and
I could put it in a row,
and I could take
the other column and I
could put it in a row,
and I create a tensor and
then I could transpose it.
All right? So I tell it,
oh, here are these rows.
Make sure they're
consecutive in memory.
And I'm like ha ha, that
row is actually a column,
but it won't want
to move it just
because I transposed it.
So if I do it like this, then
it'll be laid out in memory,
one column followed by
other column. Yeah, a
question right here.
Yeah, it should be a
constant time, right?
Maybe there's like
other packages
that are not but like Insight,
Pitorch or Numpy, it'll be
a constant time because
it's not actually
doing any real work.
Absolutely, I agree with you.
Yeah, and that's valuable
in and of itself.
Plus it's valuable
for this trick.
Yeah, thank you for
calling that out.
Other questions people
have about this trick,
you can take control
of it, right.
In the end, right? I created
this tensor in two
different ways.
Any math I do on it or any
calculations I do with it,
I'm always trying to get
exactly the same values,
but they're good at different
kinds of operations.
All right, so what you can do
is you can think about it.
Am I going to be
looking at a lot of
rows or a lot of columns?
And then you can choose, you can
have some control
over how you want
to lay out your data to
get good performance.
All right, what questions
people have about that trek?
All right, great
trick when you're
working with
matrices of numbers,
right, Which is often
a lot of what we do.
We're also often working with
other data types like strings,
Strings I think could
even trickier, right?
So on this picture I'm showing
three different ways that
I could organize a
list of strings.
I guess I might call
it a collection
because maybe it's an
array, maybe it's a list.
Whatever different
ways I could have
a sequence of strings, a, B,
and C. The first ways I can
have a linked list, right?
I could have like a
little node object.
It could contain a,
and then it could have
a pointer or a reference
over to the next one.
That could contain B,
and then that could have
a pointer to the next one.
I could lay those out.
Maybe I could have
a compact array
of references to strings
that are showing up
in different places.
Or maybe I could just lay out
all my strings one after the
other in the same place.
Which of these is going to
be the most cash friendly?
Yeah, I see a few people.
Maybe somebody can just
raise their hand and vote.
Yeah. Do you want to say Yeah,
I think the last one will
be most cash friendly.
Right. Because if I'm
accessing all these strings,
right, then they're
going to fit into
the fewest possible
cache lines, right?
Length lists are so
awful for caches, right?
Because it's almost like
you're guaranteed you're
always jumping to a different
cache line here and there.
This second one down
here is what you're
generally going to see like
in Java or Python, right?
That you generally
have a array and
it just has references
to somewhere else.
Really, the only
time you would have
like a fast array is when it
contains primitive values
that are in line, right?
That last one is the fastest,
but there's lots of
questions about how you
actually pull that off.
If I lay all the strings
like end to end,
like how do I tell like
this string ended and
the next one began?
If I want to say like grab
the string at index five,
that's kind of a hard
thing to do, right?
Because each of these strings
has a different length,
it's hard to calculate
where it is.
And then finally, with strings,
we often will have like
none or null values, right?
That's a very
natural thing to do
when you have an
array of references.
But how do I represent
that in here?
Right, So in general,
when you're programming,
you don't often end up
with this nice scenario
that you would like, right?
And so then enter per
little history on Pero.
It was started by the
person who made pandas.
How I know like people come
out of 320 have Don Panda.
How many people have
like some pandas
experience prior to this course?
So maybe half of you, right?
Pandas has lots of
great features.
It's fairly easy to use, right?
And it's really like, they're
just trying to make it
easy to jump in and start
messing around with data.
And I think that performance was
kind of considered
like after the fact.
So Piero started by
the same person with a
different perspective
of let's just make sure
everything is really, you know,
cash efficient and takes
advantage of the
latest CPU features,
all this stuff and they
haven't added all
these features but
if you're doing
something that were
performance really matters,
Piero would be much
better than say
pandas maybe eventually they'll
converge and we'll have
the best of both worlds.
So they have lots of
different data structures
called a rays for
different types.
And then they can have
tables where the table,
each column is one
of these arrays.
So let me just show you how they
would implement a string array.
They would take a few
different regions
of consecutive memory.
The first one looks like what
we saw in the last slide.
They would take all
the strings and
just lay them end
to end like this.
And that looks the same
as up here, right?
So Fubo bar and
all baths, right?
That's what they would
lay out down here.
But then they want to be
able to quickly tell you,
give me the string
at index five.
And so what they'll
do is they'll have
another region of
consecutive memory.
And they'll say the first string
is from index zero to three.
The next string is from
index three to six.
And then so on and so
forth, right that straight.
Because they can quickly jump in
here and find a string
at a specific position,
they can figure out where
is the start and
end of that string.
So the strings are consecutive,
and then these indexes
are consecutive.
And then the last piece is
that they want to support.
All right, and so
how do they do that?
They have something
called a bit map.
The bitmap has ones and zeros.
Ones means it's valid,
zero means it's not valid.
So not valid means it's
like a null or none.
So reading this from the left,
I see there's four
ballads and then a null.
And that's the same as up here,
there's four ballads
and then a null.
Right? Some other details,
they have padding.
Padding is just sites
that aren't used for
anything and so they had
this bite for the bit
map and then they
had 63 bytes over
here for padding.
Does that ring a bell?
Why do you think it's 63?
Any guesses? Yeah, right here.
The length of a cash line,
the length of a
cash line, right?
If you had these
together, they're
going to add up to a cash line.
And so their data
is going to start
right at the boundary
of a cash line, right?
So they built this
and so they are just
from the start thinking about
how can we lay things out.
So it's straightforward
in memory.
So next time I don't have
time to dig into now,
but next time I'll
do some examples.
How can we use Pierro?
Work with some data and get
some better performance
using that.
Alright grey. Have an
awesome afternoon.