Last time we were learning
about the Linux Shell
and some various programs
we could run in that Shell.
Today we're going to be talking
about pipe lines and
with a pipeline,
we can take a lot of
those little programs and
combine them together
in a chain and
do some more interesting
things in that way.
There are some
optional readings.
All these readings this
semester are optional.
They're all in the
Riley collection,
which means you
can get them free
online if you have
a library card.
How many of you have got
a library card already?
A handful of you. I'd really
encourage you to do that.
There's lots of good
resources there
besides just what we're
using in this course.
But, you know, if
you click these,
it's right to take you over
here and then you just
have to type in
your number for me.
I just had to go to the library
in person and I showed them
a piece of mail
that had my address
on it that was enough
proof for them.
Added 5 minutes, I was walking
out with a library card,
so I just get it dotted.
That'll serve you well for
the rest of the semester,
but you know, in the worst case.
Right. These are
optional readings,
so you'll be okay if
you don't have it yet.
I head over here to some slides.
1 other thing I wanted to
point out before I go,
last time we had a
worksheet and there was
also some flash cards for that.
All of those covered both
last time and today,
right on this
worksheet, for example.
A lot of these later ones are
related to some of the
things we're covering today.
So if you still have
that, whip it out.
Otherwise you could
just be taking
notes on a piece of paper.
But today is a little bit
similar to last time,
but that I'd maybe
throw you a lot of
things at you that you're
just going to have to
write down and then memorize
to be able to use it,
draw you forward.
All right, So there's
a few things I want
you to learn today.
First is how do we
actually trade together
all these different
programs and do
a pipeline that's up there?
I see a lot, not just
at this point where we're
working on the shell,
but later on when you're doing
some more data engineering tasks
similar to that is if I
have this big pipeline,
instead of just having all
the output go to the street,
how can I have that end up in
some file that's
called a redirection?
And then finally,
we're very interested
in resource consumption of
anything we're doing
this semester.
How can we measure the CPU
memory storage network
that we're using as we're
running these things.
All right, so this idea
of having the pipeline
comes from something called
the Unix philosophy.
What is Ux? Utix is actually
a whole family of different
operating systems.
Lituxst probably famous
one that people think
of the operating system running
on my Mac is also
a type of Utix.
There's other lesser
known ones like BSD,
lots of different Unix is out
there that are all kind of
similar and built out
a similar philosophy.
And so the Lipman book
that I recommended is
reading today talks about
some of that philosophy
in more detail.
And I just want to pull
two main points out
of that book of this philosophy.
The first point is that
every program you make
should just do one
thing really well.
And if you find
yourself wanting to
do a second thing or
a third thing well,
you should be
writing new programs
that do those things instead of
making your original
program more complicated.
That's in contrast to a
lot of programs we know,
like think about Excel, right?
Excel lets you try
to manage your data,
It lets you get statistics
over that data.
It lets you create plots,
it lets you cyc across
different computers.
It does all kinds of
different things.
It's a big complicated
piece of software.
And there's good and
bad in that, right?
Whether you think that's
a good design or not,
it's in violation of
this principle that Unix
tries to shoot for.
The second thing
is that if we have
all these little programs
that each do one thing, well,
we have to have
them work together
easily in order to do
more complicated things.
And so the way we do that is
that we're just going to
expect from the start that
any output from a program is
going to be the input
to another program.
As we're feeding that
what we call it,
intermediate data
between two programs.
We don't want it cluttered with
extra information or
anything like that because
that makes it more difficult for
the receiving program
to work with that.
We also don't want
to be too strict
about what formats we're doing,
so lots of different programs
can work with each other.
In the Ted book,
there's a nice example.
They walk through and they
introduce this idea of a pipe.
And a pipe is how we realize
that Tix philosophy.
And the cool thing about a pipe
is that can have all
these different programs.
Some of these you've
seen like you've
seen cat and you've seen head.
Other hears that I
won't talk about today,
like walk unique,
this little vertical bar that's
called a pipe character.
And they walk through this
example about how I can
chain all these together to
do something interesting.
In this case, what
are they doing?
Well, they have these web
logs of people visiting
some website and they're
trying to see what are
the most popular pages
on this website.
Kind of a basic
data science task.
And what's neat here is
that if you know a bunch of
different Unix
commands and you know
how to combine them together
in interesting ways,
you can do that data science
work without writing
a single slide of code and
pth or whatever, right?
So they kind of
walk through that.
But I think it's worth
reading if you're
interested in drawing a
little deeper on that.
So how do these pipes
work that connect one
program to another?
Well, they operate on something
called standard input
and standard output.
If I write a program
and then I run it,
then I have a process.
A process is just a
running program and
every process will have a
standard and standard output.
And standard is just kind of
a stream of information
ing from my keyboard.
And standard out is a stream of
information drawing to the
street that I can actually
see what happens when
I want to run two programs
and connect them.
What I'll do is I'll type
something like this down here.
I'll say a pipe character B.
And it'll start running both
processes at the same time.
Maybe on the same core,
if I only have one core,
maybe it's altered between them,
but basically they're both
running at the same time.
And what it'll do is it'll
automatically connect for me.
The standard output of
the first process is
going to feed into the standard
end of the second process.
And I could do something
more complicated than
either program could do
individually, right?
So that's a really fundamental
building block for what
we're doing today.
So to get more
complicated where I
do have examples of the shell,
but we really have
to understand that.
So I'm just trying to pause
here and let you absorb
that and see if people have
any questions already.
Yeah, question right
here, process.
Oh yeah, yeah. So
yeah, that's great.
Let's differentiate a few
of these words, right?
So first I just write a
program that's like my code.
If I start running it,
that it's a process now.
But where does it actually run?
Right? Well, my computer
has CPUs in it.
Maybe it has one CPU, many CPUs,
and then those CPU's,
it's like a chip with
a core inside of it.
And so a core is where one of
these processes could
be running, right?
Maybe I have the same number
of cores as processes,
and they're all running
at the same time.
Maybe I have more
processes than cores.
They have to take turns, right?
But I'd say like for
this point of the class,
that's to have enough detail
about what's happening.
Does that make sense?
Yeah. Thank you.
That's a great question.
Yeah. All are
questions people have.
All right? Yeah. Question
right over here.
How could it run at
the same time here?
Oh, that's a good question.
How could they run at
the same time if B is
what, relying on A.
All right, so we have
this arrow here where
they have this
intermediate data, right?
And the operating system is
in charge of that, right?
And so what might
happen is that process
is to start generating
some intermediate data.
And before it's trying
to build up that
intermediate data,
before it's even finished,
B might start eating some
of that intermediate data,
and then A might generate some
more and B might
generate some more.
Imagine they could get
into a state where they're
just kind of both running
at the same time.
You could also
imagine a situation
where one is like
faster than the other,
then one will
occasionally have to
be waiting for the
other to catch up.
But basically they could run
at the same time because
operating system is helping us
hang out to that
intermediate data.
One of the cool things is
that that intermediate data,
if I look at all
of it, it might be
bigger than the Ram I
have on my computer.
But because it's never all
in Ram at the same time,
then I can actually do this in
a very memory efficient way.
I can work with
data that's much,
much bigger than the
Ram of my computer.
Yeah. Excellent question
about intermediate data.
Yeah. Other questions
people have.
Oh, all right. You know,
this is getting more and
more complicated, right?
There's nothing that stops
you from writing, you know,
a pipes in, pipes into.
Totally fine. All right.
Now when we do this,
right, it's good for
all these programs
that are operating
to each other.
But from the human perspective,
there might be additional
error information
or troubleshooting stuff that we
don't want to feed
along the pipeline.
We just want to immediately
surface it to the user.
And so we're going
to add a third thing
in called standard error, right?
So we have one kind of input,
which is standard input
and two kinds of output,
Standard output and
standard error.
The standard in and out are
just chaining along together.
And then if I was running
a command like this,
the standard error of all of
them would be going
straight to the strain.
All right, so for example,
let's say you write
a Python program
and you just print
something out.
That print statement
is going to go
by default to stand out,
but let's say that program then
has an exception
and there's like
a stack trace that gets dumped
out that would be going
to standard error.
You know, there's
some more nuance
to that when you're
doing a print statement.
If you as a programmer
know that this is just
like an error message and
not the normal output.
If you Google it,
there's a way you
can say like I specifically want
this print statement to go to
standard error instead of
standard out so you
can control it.
It's just that by default
you're normally just
writing the standard out because
that's usually what
you want to do.
All right? So we have that
standard error there as well.
Okay? All that we've
talked about so far is
piping is going about drawing
from process to process.
A second word that people
often mix up with,
piping is similar,
is redirection.
Piping was process to process.
Redirection is process to file.
Sometimes we will want
to take the output of
our program and
save it in a file
if it's running a
long time, right?
We might want to do that and
then check back on it later.
The way we'll do
that is we'll say
the program name and then
we'll say greater than sign.
The greater sign. I'd really
just like to see it
as an arrow, right?
So a arrow and then output.
And that will redirect the
output from standard out
over to this output file.
All right, and I could
check on that later.
Maybe I just wait until it's
all done and I check on it.
Or if this program is
running for a long time.
Last time we learned
about this tail command.
With the tail command,
you can follow a file.
So I could be running this in
the background and I
might just jump on
and start tailing that file to
see what's coming
out of this program.
We sometimes want to redirect
our errors too, okay?
I won't get into too
much detail why,
but these three
things are numbered.
It goes 012 for standard
standard out and standard error.
Standard error is number two.
And the way you would
redirect that down
here is you could
say two and then arrow, right?
So you could see, I'm just
wondering one program A,
but I'm separately
redirecting standard out to
output and then standard
error to error.
You know, somebody was
asking, could you put
one in front of that greater
than I'm not really sure.
That would kind of make sense
from a logical perspective.
But you know, we don't
because they're just
trying to save typing and
90% of the time you're
interested in redirecting
the standard out.
The third thing we
can do is we might
want those inner leave
within the same file.
In that case we would say dollar
greater than and we'd send
both standard out and standard
error to the same file.
Right? So all these
things should be in
your notes because you're going
to be doing them a bunch, right?
There's just like
the simple arrow,
two arrow and arrow.
I expect you to know
what they're each doing.
Do people have any questions
about redirection?
All right, so we might be
doing all these things, right?
We might be having a
pipeline or having
this long running program
that's dumping into a file.
And those things might
take a long time.
And so we might
want to be running
these things really
in the background.
I want to be able to be
able to do other things in
the shell while it's happening.
When I normally just type
a program name in the
shell and I run it,
then it'll run for a while.
And when it's all done, I'm
going to get prompt back.
That's called synchronous.
It means that I'm
waiting until it's done.
And what we want to
have is a way to
do things that are asynchronous.
And the way I do things
asynchronous is I just put
this ampersand at the
end of the program.
And when I do that, it'll
basically in the background.
I can type other
things in the shell.
This ampersand here, I guess we
saw that with the
redirection too,
but it's just another
use of it, right?
There's no relation there.
All right, so let's
try to put all of
this together, all right?
I have everything that
I've taught you about
this morning in this
one little command.
And let me just look at this and
try to absorb it for a while.
And when you think
you understand
it well enough that
you could explain it,
then pop up a hand
and then I'll take
a volunteer and we'll talk
through what this is doing.
I've seen a few hands pop
up and draw back down.
Right now, there's no hands off.
Does anybody want
to volunteer to
explain what's going on?
Yeah, right back here.
Okay, great.
I'm just trying to echo what
you're saying. Sorry, here.
As you're saying, the
output of A is being piped
into B. Yep,
great.
So both standard error and
standard out. Going to out.
Yep, yep.
And the whole thing is
running a synchrony.
Exactly. That's what exactly
what it's doing and so
this is what the
picture looks like.
We're just changing that a long,
collecting all this output
here so we could see
what happens in the end.
The only thing that is directly
going into the screen is
the standard error from
the first one, right?
So if I wanted to,
I could redirect that to
a separate file, right?
So there's no reason I couldn't
have redirects after
each of these,
right, for their standard error.
But this is what it would
look like in the end, right?
So I expect that if I
show you a command,
you can kind of see
what the picture
looks like or vice versa.
Cool, So that one's a little bit
of a more complicated example.
Yeah, questions people have
right here. Yeah, go ahead.
The double arrow,
you mean like this
or after the redirect?
There's two. You mean
like in the command
or in the picture.
I'm just trying to
see what do you
mean for like the double arrow?
Oh, up here? Yeah. You know,
I think Okay. I see
what you're saying.
Yeah, it looks that way up here.
It doesn't look that way on
my monitor and that's why I'm
like my losing my mind.
I don't see arrow.
Yeah, I think it's just
like an artifact of
how the monitors or
the projectors sling,
but it's just meant to be one
arrow there. Nothing there.
Yeah, and I saw a couple
of other hands up.
Yeah, right here.
If I had two there.
Oh, like two arrows.
Oh, yeah, that's
a great question.
So I'll talk about that
a little bit more.
I'll do a live example later,
but I'll just briefly answer
the question too, right?
So I have this out, and
if that doesn't already
exist, it's created.
If it does exist, it
just gets wiped clean.
If I do two arrows,
then I can say like I want
to add to that existing one.
Is that what you were
asking? Okay. So sorry.
I was just actually
confused there.
Yeah. Okay. Got it. Got it.
And I saw another hand
up somewhere. Okay.
Judge, was that the same thing?
Everybody had the same
question. Yeah, right here.
So here, related to
the exactly like this one
only applies to B. Yep.
Yep. Yeah. Other
questions, people?
Yeah, right over here.
Slide yeah.
I think from last semester and
my old slides I had a
mistake on this one, Right.
I think previously I had
shown this trying down and
I was like looking at
it more this morning,
right before a lecture.
And I did a little test,
and this is what
it actually does.
So thank you for catching
that. Yeah, right back here.
Oh, you're saying,
what happens if I redirect
the standard error of
this one out as well?
I don't know. Actually, it's
a good question. I don't know.
I don't know if
it does something
reasonable and its both of them
or if one just like
overwrites the other.
I'd be nervous about I guess
we should try it, right?
I'm not sure. Yeah, I'd imagine
what you'd probably do.
Yeah, So I don't
know that question,
but I guess maybe
what you could do
to be safe would be to
redirect it somewhere else.
But yeah, it's a good question.
I don't know the answer to.
Yeah. Over here is
the Wifi is how many
people have the Wi fi do?
Yeah, I think that makes sense.
We'll skip top at if
the Wi fi is done,
that's a shame anyway.
Yeah. Other questions
people have.
Yeah, right here. Could you?
Yeah. So I'm just I n pick
on some vocabulary, right?
So if it's drawing to another
program, it's a pipe.
And if it's a file,
redirect, right?
Okay. But you were
asking about C, so Okay.
So can we pipe to another
file? Yes, absolutely.
Yep. You could pipe to A
to B to C. And so, I mean,
there's different
ways you could do,
but I think like a
common pattern, right,
is that you're going
to have a long chain
of things piped and
then at the very end,
you're going to dump
it into a file.
Yep, exactly. That's
the common tase.
Yeah. All right. Here.
All right. I'm going to take
a question here first. Yep.
Oh, oh, maybe that's
what you're asking too.
So you have to send
that standard out and standard
error somewhere, right?
It can either go to
a file or it can,
or it can be piped
to another process.
But you can't do both.
There are programs that help
you achieve the
equivalent of that.
It's like you're trying to
send it off in two
different ways.
It's called a T, so you could
do a T and send it off
in two different ways,
but like with these operators,
it doesn't do that.
You have to have
a special program that
helps you do that.
Yeah. Yeah. Great question.
Question back here.
What's that? With
the with the pipe.
Yeah. It draws left to right.
Yep, yeah, Follow up here or
get does a standard
error get piped?
There is a way to, I don't
remember the syntax for it,
but there is a way to take
your standard error and
then merge it in with
your standard output.
And that way you could
get it to both go along.
But in general like it's
drawing somewhere else.
Because that's why they
designed standard error, right?
Is because they wanted to have
a separate channel that
would not get piped along.
But there's ways you
could force it to do
that program a correct,
a standard error is
drawing straight here.
That's something I tested
this morning to
make sure I had it
right because I had a mistake
on my slides from last year.
Yep, yeah, lots of
great questions.
I love all the questions
today that people are asking.
They've all been excellent
other questions people have.
All right, cool.
I want to pop over here
and do some live demos.
Now what I'm going
to do is I'm SSH and
I'm just hit control R and I
can SSH back in sometimes,
just use this clear command when
there's too much
stuff on the screen.
And so I'm going to
introduce a command
I often use as part
of a pipeline.
And it's called C,
and it stands for word count.
What word count
does is it lets me
type things on standard
and then they'll
tell me things about
how many words I've
typed and how many letters
I've typed and stuff like that.
So I'm going to say hello world.
And then the way I say
I'm done with standard,
I'm done typing something
is I do control D,
so I'm going to hit control D
now and then it
exits out of this.
What this is telling me
is that I typed one line,
two words, and 12
characters, right?
So I can do a word
count with that.
It's very useful for
counting things.
So for example, last time we had
this big file under data
and it was station.
So remember this one.
So maybe what I
want to do is count
how many stations there
are in that file.
So I could do that,
I could cat it,
I could say data stations
dot and then pipe
that along, right?
So the standard output
of cat will be whatever
was in that file and
I can feed that to
the standard end of
word count like that.
And I see I get a
bunch of output.
Maybe you can help me
interpret this, right?
I want to see how many stations
there are. I got three numbers.
You hold up one finger if
this tells me how many stations,
Two if the second number
tells me how many stations,
and three, if the
third one does.
I'm seeing a few ones
which is track. Right?
So the first one is
the number of lines.
In this case I have one
line per station, right?
So if I'm just trying
to count the lines,
I'd use that first one
right there, right?
So about 123,000 stations
and this data set
are being monitored.
There's other flags
you can do to try to
filter it down and just
get one number output.
But if you remember
the order of them,
then I think it's
fine to just have
a little bit of
extra information.
All right, so let's take a
look at these stations again.
And let's say I'm interested in
the ones that have the
word Madison in them.
I have to pipe those to some
kind of search program.
And a search program
that's super
useful in this environment
is called grap.
Grap does search for us,
so I'm going to
grap to search for
everything that has the
word Madison in it.
And I can do all this output
like that. All right?
So I could do that and I
could do things
like I could say,
pipe it further, right?
I could say show me the first
ten that are in Madison.
Now, you might have
noticed that some of
these are not actually Madison,
this one's Madisonville.
And so what I could do is
there's no reason I can't
have multiple processes in
my pipeline that are based
on the same program.
So I could have another G Rap.
What I want to do now is
actually eliminate this one.
So I want to do an
inverse search,
and the way I do an inverse
search is I say V, right?
So I can do that,
and that will show
me all the ones
that say Madison,
but are not Madisonville,
right? I could do that.
This is case sensitive, right?
If I make this all lower case,
I may be getting some
different results.
If I don't care about the
case, then I could say,
oh, let's do case
sensitive, right?
And I may be getting them again.
I have some that are lower case
and some that are upper case.
Word count should
be in your notes,
should be in your notes.
These flags case insensitive
and inverse search,
those should be in your notes.
Those are very helpful things.
Often we're going to be grapping
over will be the output
of some program.
We might be running, this
program that we deployed.
And it like blow all
this information
and we want to grap through
it to try to figure out,
well, what is useful
within that information.
It's kind of a quick and easy
way to search for some things.
Any questions about
that pipeline?
Yeah, Question right here.
I don't know what F crap
does. Yeah, I don't know.
If I'm trying to
learn a new command,
then I might do
something like F crap
and then I could read about it.
What does F crap do?
Okay. I guess it's
the same as rap,
so it saves you typing a flag.
And I guess I could dig in that
deeper and try to figure out
what does It's fixed strings
and I don't want to get oh,
so not regular expressions.
That's kind of
interesting, right?
So normally Rap does
regular expressions.
How many have you seen regular
expressions somewhere?
Right. So I guess it's
a version that does not
regular expressions.
Cool. And that's the way I
didn't know what F grap was,
but that's how you dive
in, in this environment.
You started using the manual
pages and you kind of just
like read through them
and that's how you
become proficient in
this environment.
Yeah, thank you
for the question,
other questions people have.
All right, so a bunch of
these examples that I've
been doing started with T,
because I'm starting
with the dataset.
Another thing that you
can do is to find it.
Well, it does a lot of things,
but maybe I'll talk
about here is it
looks at a directory, say
the current directory.
It just dumps out everything
inside of that directory, right?
So I could just
explore recursively
everything that I have here.
Again, that's a great,
that's a great way to
search through files.
Can anybody suggest a pipeline
that I could use that would
help me find all
the TXT files here?
Should keep typing after this.
Yeah, right here.
Great, dot, dot. Sounds great.
Right? So then I can find all of
those just like that, right?
So it's a great way to
search around for files.
It doesn't look inside of them,
but it helps me find
where those files are.
Another thing I could
do in this case,
I kind of got lucky because
there was no.in the middle.
But if I wanted to use
regular expressions,
some of you might remember
that $1 sign means end.
So I could do that as well too.
And if I was getting too many
matches, I could find that.
Right.
So this is just a great way
to kind of explore around
your files when
you're in the shell
and explore what's
inside of them.
A. Right. Cool. Any
questions so far?
The dollar sign. Okay, so great.
So this is a regular
expression and so this
means that it has
to be the end of
the string in the
regular expression.
Whereas if I did, this
would be saying it has to
be at the beginning
of the string, right?
And I don't remember, I just
remember a few of those too.
There's like regular expression
of the whole big
language, right?
So you can memorize a bunch
of those if you want to,
but if you are comfortable
with regular expressions,
you can use them in
this environment.
Yeah, question right here.
So yeah, that's a good question.
Can you use it for more than
that? And the answer is yes.
And I guess I start off
with that Unix philosophy.
Each, each program does
one simple thing. Well.
Right. And I think it's a little
aspirational and I
feel like a lot of
these programs like find
a bunch of stuff has
creeped in, right?
So I feel like modern find
can do a little bit of
things that rap can do too.
So I don't love that,
but I don't know.
I guess I'm teaching
the subset of
these tools that kind
of matches the vision,
right? But it's
messier than that.
A lot of them have extra
features that have creeped in.
Yep, yeah, excellent question.
Yeah, other questions
people have.
All right, cool.
So let's try doing a redirect.
Now what I want to do is I
want to build up a dataset.
I'm going to call it
the Midwest Dataset of
all the stations that are
in Wisconsin or Illinois.
And so the way I can do this
is I can tat out my data,
my stations again and
I am doing a grap
for Wisconsin like this.
Then I want to redirect
that into Midwest,
Midwest T. I'm going to do that,
and then maybe I'll just peek
inside of that to make
sure it looks good.
All right. That
looks pretty good.
That's cool. Let me add
some Illinois to it.
Now, if I just run
this right now,
the problem I have is that
since that file already exists,
it's trying to wipe it clean.
Before I do that, somebody
raised this question earlier.
What does the double arrow mean?
That was a question I had
misunderstood for a bit.
But if I do the double arrow,
it'll be in a pen mode.
And what that means is
that it's trying to add
all those new things to
the end of the file.
So if I look at the head of
the file, it's still Wisconsin.
And if I look at the
tail of the file,
then it's Illinois, right?
So I can run all of
that to build this.
Maybe what I might
want to do, right?
Let's say this is something
I have to do daily.
Let's say that this keeps
changing and I want to
keep repeating this.
I might want to turn this into
a little shell strip
that is easy to run.
So what I'm going to
do first, I'm going to
run the history command and
I'm going to see the
things I've already run.
And I can grab a
couple of these here.
This is how I built
up that dataset.
And what I'll do now
is I'm going to make
a new file called Midwest,
and I'm going to paste
those things in.
I'm going to delete some
of this other stuff.
It gives me like a number of
what command number
it was. Right.
But I could put all
those little commands in
there and then my
goal is that I,
you know, I want to be
able to just do like make
Midwest dot like that.
But I'm getting a
permission denied.
I'm going to do this LSL,
I'm wondering if anybody
can help me out.
It's a bit of a review, how
can I make it so I can run
that shell command?
Yeah, way back here.
Yeah, I want to add
execute permissions
and what command do I use?
Ch model. Okay, great.
Ch mode and add
execute permissions.
And then I want to
do that on make
Midwest does that makes sense?
And then the other
thing I have to do
is I think this will
work just like it is.
But I like to usually say like,
who specifically
am I doing it to?
Is it like the user
group? Yeah, go ahead.
User. Okay, let's do it to
the user. So I'm
going to do that.
And then I can see here
that it says, great,
so the owner is TRH,
that's me, and these are
my three permissions.
So I have read, execute.
Before I did that, I only had
read and write, so
that seems good.
You can also say, I
have a little bit
of a clue that it's cubicle
now because it says Make
Midwest. So let me just try.
I'm gonna remove the Midwest
file and then I'm going to do
a Make Midwest and then
cool it, remade it for me.
Right. So I could automate that.
I don't have to do all
that typing every time
I have that little
handy program.
Yeah, a question right here.
Use pseudo. Could I use pseudo?
That's one of the cases
where a pseudo won't work
because even though I'm
running it a pseudo,
it doesn't look
like it's a program
that should be executed.
Yep, so that's one
of the cases where I
don't wouldn't pseudo
wouldn't help.
Yep. Yeah, thank you
for clarifying that.
Cool. Now on this computer,
right, I have bash.
I'm in bash right now.
That shell let me
exit out of bash.
There's also H, right?
I'm going to exit out of that.
Maybe there's other shells
as well that I don't
even know about right now.
It's choosing one of
them to run that.
And that's probably fine because
it's a simple enough program.
It probably does the same
thing in all of them.
But I wanted to specifically in,
so if I want to do that, I
figure out where bash is.
What demand would I run to?
Figure out where on my computer
that is? Yeah, go ahead.
Yeah, I would say bash.
Excellent. I found that.
So, this is the
program that I want
to use to interpret what
this SH file means.
And then where would
I put that in?
How would I use that information
to actually make it?
Yeah, right here. A
line, a cheb line.
Great. So let's draw,
edit my Make Midwest.
And we can put a abang
line at the top.
A habe line is always
a pound signed and
an exclamation mark.
And now when I run this,
I guess it runs the same,
but I know it's actually
running in bash.
Alright, cool.
Any questions about running
these shelf strips? Yeah,
question right here.
Good question.
I noticed that directories
execute permissions,
so what happens when you put
execute a directory? Oh, great.
Okay, great. So you notice
that a lot of these directories,
I think all of them have
the execute permissions.
So that has a slightly
different meaning
in the context of a directory.
So I would have to review it,
but I'm pretty sure that
execute for a directory
means I have the ability to
create and delete files.
But we don't actually
execute a directory itself,
they're just like reusing
it for whatever reason
instead of using a
different symbol.
Yeah, excellent question.
Yeah, other questions
people have.
All right, cool.
So let me take a peek here.
I want to shift a gears a little
bit here and talk about running
processes and checking up on
how many resources they're
using, that sort of thing.
And so I'm going to go
back to this program I
had last time, count dot py.
You might remember that
running count dot.
We'll just tell me how
many stations are in,
in that file And it's, I
was going to do it again.
What I'm going to
do or I've already
done is I intentionally
made it slow.
So for every station a counting,
it's just trying to
sleep for 1 second.
Because I want to
show you how you can
deal with slow running programs.
How can you kind of peek
on what they're doing?
How can you run them
in the background?
How can you kill
them if you need to?
All right, so I'm going
to come back here
and what I'm going to do
first is I'm going to,
when I run it, I want
to run it like this
so that I have my shell here and
I can do other things, right?
So there it is, running
in the background,
I might want to have
some commands that I
can use to check what
is currently running.
One of those commands is PS,
LS list files, PS
list processes.
Ps should absolutely
be in your list
of list of notes, and
there's not many here.
I guess maybe this is it,
but it's a little hard to tell.
There's a couple of flags
I normally give it.
One is that I do a S
a and what a beans is not just
my current user
but all the users
on this virtual machine.
And not that there's
multiple humans on it,
but it could be that there's
some background stuff
running as a different user.
Right? So I do that, I get
a little bit more there.
The other thing I might
want to run is x,
and this is going to
give me a lot more.
So all these things up here are
associated with a shell
that I was operating in.
If I do x, I say I
really want everything,
not just the ones that are
currently associated
with a shell.
And so now I can do all
these different processes
that are running on my system.
These are just flags.
And so I could do
in the other order,
it does exactly the same thing.
Ps is a little bit strange.
I think normally when
people do flags,
they have a dash there
for whatever reason
they were a rebel and they
just said, we're not
going to do that.
But PSA X is something
that I'm running all
the time, right?
To just see what I have there.
Now what I might do, right?
I have all these things
and I want to figure out
which process was the
one that I was running.
So this is one
that I'll run very
commonly in
conjunction with grap.
I'll grap count.
And then I can see,
there it is, right?
It's a little bit funny
because this program,
right, it actually sees
itself running, right?
So it finds itself, and
then it actually finds
the program here.
This number over here
is what I call the
process ID for that
running process.
All of these have a process ID.
If I want to, if this
is running too long
or taking too many
resources, I can kill it.
So I can kill the
process ID, right?
The process ID.
And in this case,
I'm just going to copy that
down. Right, So I'm
going to paste that.
And I'm going to
take a look again.
And now I see it has
exited. So that's good.
I was able to kill it now
when we kill something.
And
Linux, what it does is it
sends something called
a kill signal to that
process to end it.
And there's different
kinds of kill signals.
There's a very polite kill
signal which is the default.
And that is basically saying
like please stop running.
And then the program
can get that.
The program can
decide, okay, well,
first off, the
program can decide,
I'm going to ignore that,
I'm going to keep running.
What it should do though
generally is say,
okay, you want me
to stop running?
I'm going to clean
up all my resources,
maybe I have some
temporary files.
I'm going to delete
that kind of thing.
It'll try to clean
up very nicely.
And this kill that I just gave,
it was the very polite one.
Sometimes you're
going to be dealing
with programs that have
a bug or are somehow messed
up and you'll kill them and
they do nothing, right?
So we have to send a
different kill signal.
The different kill signals have
different numbers and
the most aggressive
one is nine kill.
Nine is trying to
make sure it stops
running whether
the program wants
to or not. So I'm
going to do that.
Well, it was already stopped,
but there's no way
out of that one.
I just gonna have
to stop running.
I wonder if anybody's
ever seen this before.
Well, I guess any
questions first?
Yeah, right back here. Yeah,
that's a great question.
Right. Like so the reason you
don't want to do it is that
it might be extra
resources left open.
Maybe something's kind
of left in a mess.
And so, yeah, maybe there's
like some temporary files
that don't get
deleted or whatever.
It tend tend to leave things
in a weird state, right?
But still use it all the time
because I'm always using
programs that don't do
what I want and they
just are hung up.
Right. So sometimes you
just got to use, right?
Yeah, yeah, follow
up. What's that?
Oh, how do you recover?
Well, I guess like I mean,
there's some resources
like let's say
it's like a socket connection
over the Internet.
Some of the stuff like that,
like when a process dies,
those resources die with it.
But it could be right if
it's like about files
that are long term that it
might just be messed up.
So hopefully, fingers crossed,
the program can deal with
starting up and have things kind
of in a dirty state, right?
But sometimes it becomes
a real pain and
you have to figure
out what's going on and
clean it up yourself.
Most of the time it'll just
kind of works out. Okay.
Right. Because I have
some trolled files,
I don't really hurt anybody,
but. But yeah, absolutely.
I've seen cases where
it creates a real mess.
Yep, yeah, excellent questions.
Yeah, Over here A
means all users,
and X means not
just the terminal,
but other things
that are running in
the background that's
like those two together.
We'll give you a
pretty comprehensive
list of the processes running.
Did I see another hand
up over here somewhere?
I thought there was another
hand up. Any other hands up.
All right, cool.
So I was able to kill that.
This is killing by process ID.
Another thing you
can do is you can do
a kill and then a name, right?
So this would be
the process name.
And let me just take a
look at this one up here.
Count was an argument,
the program that's actually
running Python three,
so if I wanted to kill that one,
I could have said Python three.
Right? And then
that would do it.
I could also do a dash
nine with that one.
In some cases that's
like easier because you
don't have to mess
around figuring
out what the process idea is.
The downside of this
one is that if I have
other things that are running
with Python three as well,
other Python programs, it
just like kills all of them.
So not always what you want,
but I find myself using both
of these all the time
on a regular basis.
Alright? Any questions people
might have about
killing processes?
Yeah, right here. What? Oh,
who sets the process name?
Well, I think that when I say
like, which Python three.
So it's just like
a program here.
Right? And so that's going to
be normally the name of it.
There's a little
bit more nuanced,
like there's a way
that you could start
a process with a name
different than the
name of the program.
But that'd be kind of an
unusual situation, right?
Like 99% of time
it'll just be the name of the
program you were running.
And that's why kill you,
kind of catch up more stuff
than you want because
there might be
a bunch of processes launched
from the same program.
Yeah, there are questions
people have. All right.
Some of you might
have seen this.
I don't know if
anybody has ever been
like running like
Jupiter Notebooks
or Jupiter Lab and you
hit like control C.
And then it will
say again like oh,
hit control C again if you
really want to accent.
Has anybody ever seen
that few of you?
Right? That shows that the
control C is the polite kill.
Right? Because if
it was a kill nine,
they would have never had
a chance to ask you
anything again.
It would have been drawn, right,
but it kind of caught
that in it said,
okay, well I can try
to do something here.
All right, great. So we
talked about processes.
Now let's talk about the
resources that they use.
There's an old program
called To that would show
you the processes that are using
the most resources is a
little bit of a pain to read.
More popular is H top.
That stands for human top.
I'm going to run
that and then I can
see how my CPU and
memory is being used.
Right up here, I see
that there's 2 bars
and what that means is
that this machine I'm on
has two CPU cores
that are running.
And right now they're
both very idle, right?
There's not much running there.
Here, I can see
how much memory I have
and how much I'm using.
I have almost 2
gigabytes and I'm
using 259 megabytes of that.
If you look at the
size of the bar,
I mean it looks closer to half
which doesn't quite
line up the numbers.
The reason is that it's just
counting the green here.
The grain is the data that's
actually actively being
used by my processes.
The other stuff is cash,
which you talk about,
but the idea there is that
maybe I read like a file from
disc before and it's just
keeping a copy and Ram
and case I need it again.
But I'm not really
using that much memory.
I could free it up if I had to.
That's why the bar
doesn't line up with
what the numbers are.
And then down here I
can see that there's
all these different processes
that are running, right?
And so if you wanted to,
you could sort these, right?
You can see there's
like F six would let
me sort and I could figure out
which processes are using
the most CPU or the most memory.
So I think, you know,
a common occasion
during office hours is
people come in and
they're like, oh,
my virtual machine
is like frozen
up or it's like everything's
running really slow.
Right? One of the first
things I do is I'll look
at H top and try to see like,
well, what are they using?
If it's not obvious
what is using it,
then we might dig into this
and try to figure out,
well, what specifically
is using those resources?
Usually they know,
obviously it was
like their program
they started running.
I think it's just a good
thing to have open,
like running most of the
time to build intuition.
I think it's really
fun. Like you're
like writing some
code and running it.
And then you have
that on the side.
And you start to get
an intuition like,
oh, well, that thing,
Iran is really slow
or this other thing I
ran is very efficient, right?
So that's a good way to
build some intuition.
All right. So that
was CPU and memory.
Let's talk about storage, right?
All these commands,
right? You just got to
get them in your notes
and memorize them.
We can check storage
capacity usage with
a tool called DF and it
looks like this, right?
A lot of these
numbers are a little
hard to read and so I'm
going to pass in
for human readable.
And it'll show me now in like
gigabytes or megabytes,
things like that,
There are a bunch of different
file systems on here and we're
eventually talking
about what that
means and how they
all work together.
One of the things I could
do is I could just say,
let's do this for
the file system,
for my current directory.
So I could say dot and
then it's a little bit
easier to see what's going
on. So what does this mean?
I have a 25 gigabyte disk
on my virtual machine.
I've used 4 gigabytes of
it and I have 21, 21 free.
Right? Let's keep
an eye on that.
You might be getting
law on disk space
and you might have to
delete some stuff.
When I need to
delete some stuff,
what I do is I use another tool.
So this was DF DU will
show me a bunch of
information about how much space
is being used in
different places.
It's a disk utilization, again,
I'm going to do
human readable on it
and there's some other
flags I will typically use.
I'll use for a summary
and I might say what
directory I'm on and I
will say this home
directory I'm in right
now is using 42 megabytes.
Right? So not that
much, honestly.
Right? This is not why I'm
using those 4 gigabytes.
I might say star and
then I could say that,
you know of that 42 megabytes,
21 megabytes is in
that data directory.
So if you're running lung space,
you can kind of browse around.
And that's your job
to clean some stuff
up and stay within the
space you have, right?
All right. That's storage,
the four resources network.
And I'm trying to show you
a command that's going to
be really useful later.
Not everything
about it will make
sense and we're
going to revisit it.
But I think it's
important enough.
I want to show it
multiple times.
It is called LS 0 F,
and it stands for
List Open files,
and putting files
in quotes here,
because there's a saying
in Linux that
everything is a file,
and so network connections
are actually files,
even though we don't normally
think of them that way.
And so this is a really good
tool to see what's going on
in terms of networking resources
and in particular port numbers,
which we're going to
be talking a whole
bunch more about, right?
So I'm going to
do LS OF that has
all these files
open from all kinds
of different programs,
lots of output.
If I do pseudo, it'll
give me even more output.
But what I want to
do is I want to
pass on this flag and say TCP.
And TCP is trying to
specifically narrow us down
to one of the most common tins
of network communication.
We'll be talking
more about what that
means later, but I can do this,
I can see a bunch of
different processes that are
running and the connections
that they have.
I'm really going
to be interested
in something called
port numbers.
And in a lot of these
cases they're hiding
port numbers from me with these
cute little names like domain.
And so I'm going to pass and
now it'll give me
actual numbers here.
Right? So a really
common thing we're,
you'll be doing
later this semester.
I'm going to talk more
about port number,
so don't worry if it's
a little confusing.
But we're often want
to say like, okay,
what I'm running this program,
what port numbers is it using?
So let's just do
a quick exercise.
What, based on this output,
what port number is SSHD using?
Yeah, alright here, 22.
Yep. Ssh D is using port 22,
Al, right, so I can see here's
SSHD. Excellent, and there's 22.
And if I wanted to, I could
have even just wrapped
this and kind of narrowed
it down, right, so
we can do that.
That's trying to do
something we do again and
again this semester as we're
deploying these things.
Because port numbers are
how we're going to connect
different programs and get
them to talk to each other.
So we're going to have
to look that in kind of
information up and I'll
bring this command back.
Right. Because
it's so important,
I just wanted to show it for
the first time for completeness.
Awesome. All right, well,
I hope you all we'll have
a great evening and
maybe get a chance
to play with some of these
commands on your own.
Feel free to come up and chat
if you have any questions.